<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Hawkinslab</title>
<link>https://UNL-Hawkins-Lab.github.io/Hawkinslab/thoughts/blog.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://UNL-Hawkins-Lab.github.io/Hawkinslab/thoughts/blog.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.3.361</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 May 2024 05:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Schumacher On Prediction</title>
  <dc:creator>Jason Hawkins</dc:creator>
  <link>https://UNL-Hawkins-Lab.github.io/Hawkinslab/thoughts/posts/05-28-2024/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Best known for his work on small-scale economics, in the same work (Small is Beautiful), E.F. Schumacher provides one of the best discussions on prediction that I have seen to date. It is also an excellent example of <em>semantics</em> applied in its true sense, rather than the typical pejorative meaning associated with the term in many discussions.</p>
<p>Schumacher distinguishes prediction along three dimensions using a set of <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?2%5E3%20=%208"> cases as follows:</p>
<div class="columns">
<div class="column" style="width:50%;">
<ol type="1">
<li>Act Past Certain</li>
<li>Act Future Certain</li>
<li>Act Past Uncertain</li>
<li>Act Future Uncertain</li>
</ol>
</div><div class="column" style="width:50%;">
<ol start="5" type="1">
<li>Event Past Certain</li>
<li>Event Future Certain</li>
<li>Event Past Uncertain</li>
<li>Event Future Uncertain</li>
</ol>
</div>
</div>
<p>Let us first discuss <em>acts</em> and <em>events</em>. The first (acts) are active and “within the control of the planner”, while the second (events) are passive and “outside the control of the planner”. The planner may be able to forecast events and their influence on plans, but they cannot be part of the plans. <em>Plan</em> and <em>estimate</em>, while appearing to apply to the future only, are often applied to past events. For example, “I shall not visit Paris without a plan” can mean “I shall arm myself with a street plan for orientation” - case 5 because the plan construction is a certain event that occured in the past outside your control. Alternatively, “I shall arm myself with a plan which outlines in advance where I am going to go and how I am going to spend my time and money” - case 2 or 4 depending on the certainty of said plans. Similarly, estimate may refer to either the past or the future. Past events often remain uncertain due to measurement error and other factors.</p>
<p>Having spent the better part of the last decade studying human behaviour and forecasting it under alternative conditions, I found Schumacher’s classification system encapsulated much of what I believe about the ability to forecast behaviour. I follow Schumacher’s definitions with a short commentary.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Full predictability (in principle) exists only in the absence of human freedom - i.e., in “sub-human” nature. The limitations of predictability are purely limitations of knowledge and technique.</li>
</ol>
<p>That is, if we assume no human freedom and deterministic choice, 100% accurate prediction is feasible provided we have all the available information and the correct model structure. I have the sense that many of my field are of the opinion that <em>Big Data</em> and <em>Artificial Intelligence</em> bring us daily closer to this reality. I am not so readily convinced of this fact.</p>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li>Relative predictability exists with regard to the behaviour pattern of large numbers of people doing “normal” things (routines).</li>
</ol>
<p>In transportation modeling, we would call this travel on a typical day and aggregate (4-step) demand modeling.</p>
<ol start="3" type="1">
<li>Relatively full predictability exists with regard to human actions controlled by a plan which eliminates freedom, e.g., railway timetables.</li>
</ol>
<p>I like this example for obvious reasons.</p>
<ol start="4" type="1">
<li>Individual decisions by individuals are in principle unpredictable.</li>
</ol>
<p>I agree with this statement. I see the shift towards disaggregate modeling as a means to increase prediction accuracy and nuance for large numbers of people (point 2 above) rather than a suggestion that we can accurately predict the individual decisions at which the model is set up.</p>
<p>Schumacher then touches on a point that has recently seen great interest in the transportation demand modeling community - uncertainty. He states “all long-term forecasting is somewhat presumptuous and absurd, unless it is of so general a kind that it merely states the obvious”. Schumacher emphasizes the need to focus on modeling as a tool for <em>exploratory calculations</em> rather than <em>forecasting</em>, per se. In forecasting, we are stating that a certain set of conditions will be the case in 20 years time or, in the slightly more nuanced form of the same, that differences from current conditions will have some absolute value. E.g., we forecast future traffic and make statements about the difference in traffic on particular roads given a change in infrastructure. An exploratory approach includes multiple potential futures and considers the “long-term effect of certain assumed tendencies”. Schumacher uses a development example. He proposes a backcasting exercise to explore potential pathways for the uplift of underdeveloped nations. “What would be the required output of foodstuffs, fuels, metals, textile fibres, and so forth? What would be the stock of industrial capital?” Many new assumptions would be necessarily along the way and the outcome would be a set of feasibility studies to indicate the most feasible among alternative <em>patterns of development</em>. The discussion here is again (partially) one of semantics. We must recognize that long-term forecasts are infeasible, while long-term feasibility study can be a worthwhile exercise.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>prediction</category>
  <category>estimation</category>
  <category>semantics</category>
  <guid>https://UNL-Hawkins-Lab.github.io/Hawkinslab/thoughts/posts/05-28-2024/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 28 May 2024 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://UNL-Hawkins-Lab.github.io/Hawkinslab/thoughts/posts/05-28-2024/banner.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Jevons Paradox</title>
  <dc:creator>Jason Hawkins</dc:creator>
  <link>https://UNL-Hawkins-Lab.github.io/Hawkinslab/thoughts/posts/04-26-2024/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>William Stanley Jevons was a 19th century English economist and logician. He made extensive contributions to the field, yet is perhaps best known for his eponymous paradox. Jevons Paradox arises when technological progress increases the efficiency with which a resource is used (reducing unit consumption), but the falling marginal cost of use induces increases in demand such that aggregate resource use is increased, rather than reduced. Engineers are, in general terms, believers in the benefits of technology. Efficiency gains are professed to solve any number of social and environmental ills. E.g., autonomous vehicles will solve traffic congestion and improved safety through their elimination of fallible human drivers. Consider the narrative regarding the population theory of another late 18th century/early 19th century economist - Thomas Malthus. Malthus predicted population collapse in response to population growth outstripping agricultural productivity growth. Thus far, his prediction has not come to pass partially due to technological progressing, including the 20th century Green Revolution (led by Norman Borlaug and others), which relieved starvation concerns - yay! Techno-optimists reference this success as an exemplar of why technology will save us. Furthermore, the so-called Environmental Kuznets Curve (named for yet another economist, Simon Kuznets) anticipates GDP becoming decoupled from environmental impacts as a nation moves from an industrial to a post-industrial economy.</p>
<p>Let us take a look at the Kuznets Curve in the context of Jevons Paradox. If we assume a steady state economy, then it may be the case that environmental impacts will decrease as a function of technological progress. By a steady state economy, we mean a constant stock of capital and fixed population.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://UNL-Hawkins-Lab.github.io/Hawkinslab/thoughts/posts/04-26-2024/jevons_1.svg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:50.0%"></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Of course, we do not exist in a steady state economy, global population continues to grow (rising from 6 billiong to 8 billion people in my own lifetime). While natural resources are a fixed stock (we will return to this topic on many occassions), our rate of resource consumption has not declined as a function of technological progress. Rather, we continue to consume increasing quantities of materials and energy, which represent the fundamental building blocks of human society. Another way to term a steady state economy is that its size is a non-stationary function of time. Stationarity will be a familiar term to those with a background in statistics or econometrics - refering to the lack of equilibrium about a fixed level of resource consumption in this case. With GDP encouraged to grow without limit, Jevons Paradox quickly comes to bear. Technological progress will get us only so far when faced with the tasks of overcoming a non-stationarity system.</p>
<p>We can consider the problem from the perspective of aggregate environmental impact vs.&nbsp;marginal (unit) environmental impact. Jevons Paradox shows us that individuals will increase their environment impacts (vis-a-vis more consumption) in response to technological innovations that reduce the marginal cost, or material and energy requirements - i.e., increasing aggregate individual impacts. At the same time, additional individuals (i.e., population growth) compounds the impacts, even should these new individuals consume resources at a diminished rate.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://UNL-Hawkins-Lab.github.io/Hawkinslab/thoughts/posts/04-26-2024/jevons_2.svg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:50.0%"></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>So what can be done? The first step is to recognize myopia in our collective perspective on resource consumption as engineers, economists, policy-makers, and inhabitants of this planet. Classical valuation methods cannot account for these impacts, at least as long as they exist within an epistemology founded in growth as a positive property of human society rather than as a normative value.</p>
<p>I hope to continue to examine these topics in greater depth, not for professional promotion (unlikely absent a large grant to build ecological philosophy widgets with my graduate students) but rather for personal edification and sanity. I would like to reflect on value systems, morality, and social change. I am also interested in teasing out the seeming intangibles of the engineering perspective on policy evaluation from the conventional economics-based approach, and how engineering has been drawn into the economics perspective through a lack of appropriate application of relevant theory and knowledge - e.g., entropy, biophysical limits, and system dynamics.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>environmental economics</category>
  <category>system dynamics</category>
  <guid>https://UNL-Hawkins-Lab.github.io/Hawkinslab/thoughts/posts/04-26-2024/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2024 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://UNL-Hawkins-Lab.github.io/Hawkinslab/thoughts/posts/04-26-2024/banner.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Four Horsemen of the Production Apocalypse</title>
  <dc:creator>Jason Hawkins</dc:creator>
  <link>https://UNL-Hawkins-Lab.github.io/Hawkinslab/thoughts/posts/04-21-2024/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Gary Becker begins his “A Theory of the Allocation of Time” <span class="citation" data-cites="Becker_1965">(Becker 1965)</span> with a discussion of time spent at work relative to other activities, highlighting the need for more robust analyses of uncompensated time use in economics. Little did he know that his theory and model structure would strongly influence travel behaviour and economic analysis over subsequent decades. In the 1970s, DeSerpa <span class="citation" data-cites="DeSerpa_1971">(1971)</span> and Evans <span class="citation" data-cites="Evans_1972">(1972)</span> provided among the first connections to transportation analysis. Building from DeSerpa and Evans, Jara-Díaz <span class="citation" data-cites="Jara-Díaz_2003">(2003)</span> completed fundamental work on the value of time in transportation economics. However, there is a wealth of other insights relevant to transportation analysis to be gained from Becker’s theory. I will focus on the topic of transportation service provision.</p>
<p>Being a founder of the neoclassical “Chicago School of Economics”, Becker would certainly have strong opinions on the extension of his theory to include other non-market means of production. Nonetheless, one can consider four basic forms of production: market, home, government, and commons. Market production is the exchange of a good or service for money. Home production, as defined by Becker, is uncompensated production by the household (e.g., making dinner, cleaning the bathroom, etc.). The latter two forms of production were not discussed by Becker in his 1965 paper. In the first form, government produces a good or service for use by the public, financed by tax revenue or similar sources. For example, most healthcare services in the United States are privatized and subject to market forces, whereas many other nations provide healthcare as a public service. The final form of production is in the commons. Neoclassical economic theory suggests that common resources will be exploited if not managed by state intervention or market forces via monetization. However, both Mariana Mazzucato <span class="citation" data-cites="Mazzucato_2018">(2018)</span> and Elinor Ostrom <span class="citation" data-cites="Ostrom_1990">(1990)</span> provide compelling arguments for the efficient use of common production. As one example, Wikipedia is managed in the commons as most contributors provide their services at no cost.</p>
<p>The reader may wonder: what does any of this have to do with travel behaviour? I argue that the above economic production framework can be mapped onto the transportation mode choice problem and provides valuable insights for behavioural theory and modelling methods. Home production of transportation takes the form of walking, cycling, or using one’s own vehicle. The vehicle and fuel must be purchased on the market, but the transportation service is provided by the household using personal time as the only input to production. In contrast, taxi or ridehail modes are purchased in the market from private firms (e.g., Uber, Lyft, Didi, etc.). Government provides transportation as a public service through transit. Transportation provided in the commons is less common (a nice little pun) but takes the form of carsharing and other systems wherein the service cost is shared among a pool of otherwise unaffiliated households. Each of the above transportation alternatives could manifest as the same physical mode – i.e., a small passenger vehicle. However, the behavioural and operational models differ. For example, a person may be unable to afford market production (ridehail). They may not use public production (transit) to avoid sharing a vehicle with strangers. They may be unwilling to participate in the commons (carshare) because they don’t want someone’s muddy boots in their car.</p>
<p>Being trained as a civil engineer, I am always keen to find concrete (two puns in one article is the limit) applications for theory. The modelling of autonomous vehicles (AVs) provides an application of the above theory to transportation. Many scholars make the distinction between personal AVs, shared AVs (or SAVs) provided as a public service, and SAVs provided in the market. However, in my reading, there is minimal thought given to how these operating models would function from an economic production theory perspective. Let us first focus on the first alternative. It is unclear whether to classify a personal AV as home production or market consumption – Is sitting comfortably in a vehicle while it performs the driving task pure leisure? Are you purchasing driving services in the market as a software package? The latter two alternatives provide an interesting contrast. In both cases, SAVs are provided to the household as a service. However, if we consider transportation as a public service, another economic concept may be brought to bear, termed private provision of a public good by Bergstrom et al. <span class="citation" data-cites="Bergstrom_Blume_Varian_1986">(1986)</span> . Public transit provides a subsidized travel option for low-income households and those who choose not to own a personal vehicle. The widescale deployment of SAV fleets would therefore require ridehailing operators to take on this role. The risk is that each operator may rely on other operators to serve low-income households, with the result being a Nash equilibrium that does not maximize total social utility. Government intervention is necessary to ensure an equitable distribution of mobility through incentives or regulations <span class="citation" data-cites="Sieg_2020">(Sieg 2020)</span>. Existing simulations often ignore the profit-seeking motives of private operators, assuming they match trips to minimize detour time and are agnostic to traveller income and profit maximization motives on the part of operators.</p>
<p>As a final thought on the historical distinction between private and public travel modes. The marginal private automobile trip tends to add travel time for existing travellers through congestion that slows travel speed and increases its variability. In contrast, the marginal transit trip tends to improve service for existing travellers through reduced vehicle headways and the use of higher-order transit (i.e., trains rather than buses). The latter outcome is termed as an anti-congestion effect <span class="citation" data-cites="Mohring_1972">(Mohring 1972)</span>. The trend in SAV research is toward small, automobile-style, vehicles that may be shared or used alone. This shift adds shades of gray to the public-private dichotomy. Will shared mobility exhibit the congestion effect of fthe private automobile or the anti-congestion effect of transit? Importantly, in which contexts do these new forms of mobility tend to exhibit each of these effects (i.e., there is likely a spectrum of possible impacts depending on the application of technology, local built form, and transportation infrastructure conditions)?</p>
<section id="references" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="references">References</h2>
<div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent">
<div id="ref-Becker_1965" class="csl-entry">
Becker, Gary S. 1965. <span>“A Theory of the Allocation of Time.”</span> <em>The Economic Journal</em> 75 (299): 493. <a href="https://doi.org/10.2307/2228949">https://doi.org/10.2307/2228949</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Bergstrom_Blume_Varian_1986" class="csl-entry">
Bergstrom, Theodore, Lawrence Blume, and Hal Varian. 1986. <span>“On the Private Provision of Public Goods.”</span> <em>Journal of Public Economics</em> 29: 2549.
</div>
<div id="ref-DeSerpa_1971" class="csl-entry">
DeSerpa, A. C. 1971. <span>“A Theory of the Economics of Time.”</span> <em>The Economic Journal</em> 81 (324): 828–46. <a href="https://doi.org/10.2307/2230320">https://doi.org/10.2307/2230320</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Evans_1972" class="csl-entry">
Evans, Alan W. 1972. <span>“On the Theory of the Valuation and Allocation of Time.”</span> <em>Scottish Journal of Political Economy</em> 19 (1): 1–17. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1467-9485.1972.tb00504.x">https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1467-9485.1972.tb00504.x</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Jara-Díaz_2003" class="csl-entry">
Jara-Díaz, Sergio R. 2003. <span>“On the Goods-Activities Technical Relations in the Time Allocation Theory.”</span> <em>Transportation</em> 30 (3): 245–60. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1023/A:1023936911351">https://doi.org/10.1023/A:1023936911351</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Mazzucato_2018" class="csl-entry">
Mazzucato, Mariana. 2018. <em>The Value of Everything: Making and Taking in the Global Economy: Mazzucato, Mariana: 9781610396745: Amazon.com: Books</em>. PublicAffairs.
</div>
<div id="ref-Mohring_1972" class="csl-entry">
Mohring, Herbert. 1972. <span>“Optimization and Scale Economies in Urban Bus Transportation.”</span> <em>The American Economic Review</em> 62 (4): 591–604. <a href="https://doi.org/10.2307/1806101">https://doi.org/10.2307/1806101</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Ostrom_1990" class="csl-entry">
Ostrom, Elinor. 1990. <em>Governing the Commons : The Evolution of Institutions for Collective Action</em>. Cambridge University Press. <a href="http://archive.org/details/governingcommons0000ostr">http://archive.org/details/governingcommons0000ostr</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Sieg_2020" class="csl-entry">
Sieg, Holger. 2020. <span>“Voluntary Provision of Local Public Goods and Services.”</span> In <em>Urban Economics and Fiscal Policy</em>, 90–105. Princeton University Press.
</div>
</div>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>transportation planning</category>
  <category>production theory</category>
  <guid>https://UNL-Hawkins-Lab.github.io/Hawkinslab/thoughts/posts/04-21-2024/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 21 Apr 2024 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://UNL-Hawkins-Lab.github.io/Hawkinslab/thoughts/posts/04-21-2024/banner.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>William Vickrey and Transportation Economics</title>
  <dc:creator>Jason Hawkins</dc:creator>
  <link>https://UNL-Hawkins-Lab.github.io/Hawkinslab/thoughts/posts/05-04-2018/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>William Vickrey made major contributions to a wide range of fields within the economics discipline and was recognized for his work with 1996 Nobel Prize in Economic Science. Many of his contributions fall within my interests of Urban and Transportation Economics, so I thought it worthwhile to review a few of his publications. He also happens to be the only Nobel Laureate, of which I am aware, who was borne in my home province of British Columbia. My focus will be on his work in marginal cost pricing, specifically his article “Congestion Theory and Transport Investment”, which was published in American Economic Review in 1969. This is among the first discussions of congestion pricing. His focus is on measures to relieve congestion, and the efficient allocation of public investment towards this objective. He suggests that investment does not sufficiently consider the marginal cost, and may therefore misrepresent consumer surplus as a metric for investment benefit.</p>
<p>Vickrey was one of those great geniuses who, in an off-hand comment, makes insights that would form the basis for an entire paper by others. One such case is that of bus headway, which he argued to be optimally related to demand by a square root relationship - to be proven analytically by Gordon Newell at UC Berkeley a few years later. Vickrey assumes delay to vary by the square of total volume, with no indication of an empirical reference point. This forms a cornerstone of his theory of traffic congestion. On average, a vehicle will inflict an amount of delay on other vehicles equal to the delay experienced by itself.</p>
<p>The principle situation of delay considered by Vickrey is what he terms a <em>bottleneck</em>. This is an instance of a segment of roadway that has a lower capacity than its upstream and downstream adjacent segments. The <em>bottleneck</em> is typically a function of a reduction in the number of travel lanes due to an accident or geometric constraint (e.g.&nbsp;bridge or road narrowing). Vickrey recognizes this is an atypical form of congestion, but argues for its tractable setup for analytical analysis of costs and measures of welfare.</p>
<p>He considers the example of a bottleneck on a roadway with a demand for travel of N = 7,200 commuters. It is assumed that their departure from the bottleneck is distributed uniformly over a period between <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t_a%20=%2008:00"> and <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t_b%20=%2009:00">. The critical capacity can be defined as</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%20v_m%20=%20%5Cfrac%7BN%7D%7Bt_b%20-%20t_a%7D%20=%20120%5C,%20veh/min%20%5Clabel%7Beq:mc1%7D%20"></p>
<p>If the capacity of the bottleneck is smaller than <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?v_m">, then it is impossible for all the commuters to reach their destinations at their desired arrival times. Some of the commuters will arrive at their destinations close to their arrival time, but will be required to stay in the queue for a longer time. While those who push their arrival time away from the desired arrival time, will spend relatively less time in the queue, but experience a penalty through time spent at home when they desire to be at their destination (or, if not desire, lose pay).</p>
<p>Vickrey makes a set of assumptions about value of time (VOT), which initially confused me on the basis of disutility of time - until I realized that they described activities with positive utility parameters. He defines the value of time spent at home at <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?w_h%20=%202%5C,%20cents/min">, time spent at work before the desired starting time at <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?w_o%20=%20w_p%20=%201%5C,%20cent/min">, and time spent at work after the desired starting time at <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?w_o%20=%20w_j%20=%204%5C,%20cents/min">. This means that, before the desired starting time, a person would rather be at home (greater VOT), while they would rather be at work after the desired start time. This tends to assume a wage of 2 cents per minute above the VOT for leisure (i.e.&nbsp;time spent at home). Time spent in the queue is valued at <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?w_q%20=%200%5C,%20cents/min">. With these monetary conditions, a fraction of commuters, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?r%20=%20%5Cfrac%7B2%7D%7B3%7D">, will pass through the queue during queue development. The time of maximum queue size will occur at <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t_p%20=%2008:40">, subjective to the above prices. Vickrey specifies a linear relationship for the queue size, producing a triangular shape in time and queue size, with a maximum at time <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t_p">. He suggests that a dynamic price structure be set, which eliminates the queue. The toll is set to zero at <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t_i"> and rises to a maximum, given by</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%20p_p%20=%20%5Cfrac%7BNr%7D%7Bv%7D(w_h%20-%20w_p)%20=%20%5Cfrac%7B4800%7D%7Bv%7D%20%5Clabel%7Beq:mc2%7D%20"></p>
<p>at <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t_p">, before falling to zero at <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t_j">. Commuters will leave their home at a time, such that they leave the location of the bottleneck at the same time they would leave the queue absent prices. This will distribute commuters throughout the time period in a more even manner, such that no queue forms and no commuter would be better off changing their departure time, in terms of VOT and congestion toll.</p>
<p>An interesting aspect to this result is that it has a net neutral effect from the perspective of the commuter, but produces additional revenue for the local government agency levying the toll. Revenue from the toll could be used to offset an existing flat toll or invested in long-term infrastructure improvements (e.g.&nbsp;transit or capacity expansion). Vickrey extends his study through empirical analysis of the results, consideration of alternative routes, and variation in the VOT. He provides some interesting commentary on the assessment of investments in new infrastructure. He argues that many of the new routes put forth at the time of publication based their benefit measures on increased speeds and flow volumes. These are not accurate measures of benefits to the user because they are frequently circuitous routes and do not decrease overall travel time. Vickrey argues for the application of congestion pricing as a policy lever in the cost-benefit analysis. The inclusion of such a measure would give a more accurate picture of the monetized improvement in travel time.</p>
<p>Vickrey published “The City as a Firm” in the proceedings of a conference held by the International Economic Association in 1977. The significance of this work is its early development of concepts of New Economic Geography. Vickrey identifies the importance of transportation costs and economies of scale as model inputs. The absence of transportation costs represents a futuristic notion of instantaneous movement of goods and persons. Vickrey defines economies of scale in this context as positive neighbourhood effects. This is a measure of the efficiency of proximity. If each activity could be carried out efficiently within small shops, then production could be uniformly spread throughout a region without loss of efficiency. Evidence has found neither to be the case and this is an important point in the context of autonomous vehicles (AV). They are often touted as significantly reducing transportation costs, but this argument fails on two counts. Based on the arguments of Vickrey, this argument fails to recognize the structural importance of scale economies. Such effects are wholly unaffected by the introduction of AV and economic efficiency will outweigh any desire to relocate activities to more dispersed locations. Vickrey discusses the importance of natural features in the location of our largest cities, while also recognizing that their size would be far smaller in the absence of economies of scale.</p>
<p>A related publication, in the context of the effect of AV adoption on city formation, is the book “Peak Car: the Future of Travel” by Professor David Metz at UCL. He provides a strong argument for hard limits on the speed of travel within an urbanized region. Metz argues that average commuting time has an equilibrium about 30 minutes, going back to the dawn of human civilization. While not a new argument, it is an important one and has been largely overlooked in the AV literature. These vehicles have the potential to introduce marginal increases in travel speed and therefore travel distance, but this 30 minute threshold will likely remain. Transportation costs will remain a factor in the formation and development of urban regions.</p>
<p>Vickrey assumes a perfect market in developing a model of the city as a firm but recognizes this is not an ideal assumption. Dixit and Stiglitz published their monopolistic competition model in the same year, which led to the NEG work of Krugman in the following decades (for which he scored himself a Nobel).</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>economics</category>
  <category>Canadians</category>
  <guid>https://UNL-Hawkins-Lab.github.io/Hawkinslab/thoughts/posts/05-04-2018/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 04 May 2018 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://UNL-Hawkins-Lab.github.io/Hawkinslab/thoughts/posts/05-04-2018/banner.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Our Trip to Toronto Through the USA</title>
  <dc:creator>Jason Hawkins</dc:creator>
  <link>https://UNL-Hawkins-Lab.github.io/Hawkinslab/thoughts/posts/09-11-2017/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Written after we crossed the country for my Ph.D.&nbsp;in 2017. I haven’t returned to Duluth, MN yet…</p>
<p>We just completed an exhausting 1 week tour of the northern states: North Dakota, Minnesota, Wisconsin, and Michigan. One of the major take aways for both Heather and myself was the various infrastructure we traversed in the course of our travels. I would like to discuss a bit of this, with some accomonying amateur photography.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>This was the best case of a roller joint on a steel frame structure I have ever seen. It bring back mixed feelings about days in Structure Engineering courses during my undergraduage degree. <img src="https://UNL-Hawkins-Lab.github.io/Hawkinslab/thoughts/posts/09-11-2017/DSC_0891.JPG" class="img-fluid" alt="Grand Forks, ND Bridge"></li>
<li>This was a mediocre brewery, but a great spot in Grand Forks, ND. It is situated adjacent to a major rail corridor and take full advantange. There are clear views of the trains rolling into town and by the brewery thanks to large windows looking out onto the street and alley. It was an excellent example of linking the present use of an older structure with its surrounding environment and historical industrial roots. <img src="https://UNL-Hawkins-Lab.github.io/Hawkinslab/thoughts/posts/09-11-2017/img/DSC_0897.JPG" class="img-fluid" alt="Grand Forks, ND Brewery"></li>
<li>We drove into Duluth, MN with very little knowledge of its layout and no plans as to what to visit. This is I35 passing through downtown. We pulled off the highway at a downtown exit and planned to walk somewhere for lunch. This rapidly became more of a challenge than expected as it turned out the downtown is largely commercial and wayfinding signage proved less than helpful. The interstate acts to separate the downtown from the lakeshore. It is unclear from this side of the interstate whether there are additional services on the lakeshore side of the roadway and it is clearly prohibitive to pedestrians. We were able to find a pedestrian overpass to the lakeshore, which led to a quaint lakeside retail area. We were able to find an excellent brewery (sense a pattern) called Canal Park Brewing Company. I noticed a similar patttern of the commercial centre being separated from the tourist-focused lakeshore upon arrival in Toronto. This is a model reminiscent of the days of Robert Moses in New York, with his focus on placing large-scale transportation facilities along prime waterfront real estate. <img src="https://UNL-Hawkins-Lab.github.io/Hawkinslab/thoughts/posts/09-11-2017/DSC_0946.JPG" class="img-fluid" alt="Duluth Interstate"></li>
<li>We were unable to ride the train, but it gives some incentive to return to the Duluth, MN area. It promises excellent views of the Lake Superior shore and ends at Two Harbors, MN. It feels like a disservice to my profession to miss out on an historical train ride. <img src="https://UNL-Hawkins-Lab.github.io/Hawkinslab/thoughts/posts/09-11-2017/DSC_0950.JPG" class="img-fluid" alt="Duluth Train"></li>
</ol>



 ]]></description>
  <category>travel</category>
  <category>infrastructure</category>
  <guid>https://UNL-Hawkins-Lab.github.io/Hawkinslab/thoughts/posts/09-11-2017/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 11 Sep 2017 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://UNL-Hawkins-Lab.github.io/Hawkinslab/thoughts/posts/09-11-2017/banner.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>AV Deployment, Urban DNA, and Equity</title>
  <dc:creator>Jason Hawkins</dc:creator>
  <link>https://UNL-Hawkins-Lab.github.io/Hawkinslab/thoughts/posts/07-03-2017/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p><em>Written before starting my Ph.D.&nbsp;in 2017 (July 03, 2017)…</em></p>
<p>Many questions arise for the transportation-land use modeller with the prospect of autonomous vehicles. Its effect on urban form will be heavily influenced by the manner in which it is implemented. It is probable AV will become a ubiquitous replacement of our current auto fleet, but may not be placed under personal ownership. One alternative would be a public fleet of vehicles. This has the advantage of being controlled by a single entity with a history of managing shared mobility services. Given the rapid emergence of the technology and its beginning in the private sector via automobile and technology firms, it is also likely for AV to be implemented as a set of competing services, similar to Uber and Lyft. This has advantages from the perspective of competition leading to innovation, but raises equity concerns. In addition, by placing the means of transport into private hands, there are concerns raised about privatization of infrastructure, etc. The final alternative would be a simple replacement of private automobiles, with personal ownership of each AV. These alternative implementations have the potential to influence the impact of AV on urban form.</p>
<p>My thoughts on this matter are concentrated on representing these alternative implementations in an integrated modelling framework. Do existing model frameworks have the capacity to model such changes, or are new methods required? The LUTI modelling field developed within a relatively stable transport system (i.e.&nbsp;the private automobile paradym). There is likely a need for increased dynamics in models. Rather than examining the impacts on demand of the introduction of a new interchange, we are interested in the changes in urban form resulting from a change in transportation supply and associated changes in demand. Alan Wilson is one of the founders of spatial interaction models and continues to develop innovative ideas with regards to dynamics in urban systems and their basic form. One of th concepts he considers is the idea of an urban ‘DNA’ and introduction of concepts from biological evolution into urban modelling. These types of concepts are critical in the development of models with the ability to consider seemingly large deviations from our current systems of transport. This requires a concept of fundamental rules of urban formation and growth to be operationalized in the model and not allowing oneself to be constrained by current transportation modes, etc.</p>
<p>One of the structures attributed to the introduction of the private automobile is urban sprawl, but to the history nerd this form appears long before. Without dipping too deep into history, we can see similar forms in the country estates of 18th century Britain. The ‘London Season’ was a time of the year when these nobles and other wealthy property owners would come into the city for a time to meet and put together marriages. We seem to have a natural, in our DNA, preference for solitude and personal space. Conversely, we also require proximity for social engagement, even with our rapidly developing communication technologies. Increased wealth among the middle classes has brought the ability to own a small ‘estate’ within the grasps of the every man, suggesting urban sprawl is not only a function of the automobile, but an ingrained desire that became possible through increased wealth. In the context of AV, I wonder what ingrained, DNA-based, desires and preferences will manifest themselves in our urban form. I perceive a need for better longitudinal data analysis, rather than close calibration to data from the current year. Rather than forcing the spatial structures of today onto the model, we should focus on dynamics and long-term trends. I have more confidence in the stability of the human mind than a concrete overpass with a 50 year design life, built 40 years ago. We must look to analogy in the phyical sciences in physics and biological DNA, but remember we humans are complex and dynamic systems. We should also be considering the latest concepts in economics and psychology. We must not allow ourselves to be pulled into the stream of past models, but let them guide us.</p>
<p><em>Written at the start of my Ph.D.&nbsp;(Nov.&nbsp;27, 2017)…</em></p>
<p>One aspect of AV, which has not be sufficiently assessed is the issue of social equity. Mobility is a key factor in determining social mobility (excuse the word-play) and there is strong evidence for transportation investment/quality being strongly correlated with the spatial distribution of income groups. In terms of transit usage, higher income groups tend to take fixed rail transit over bus. This has resulted in the subway map of many cities displaying a strong resemblance with income maps (see for example this CityLab article). Transportation comprises about 30% of household expenses for the poorest of North Americans.</p>
<p>This brings us to the case of AV. Some believe this innovation will be unequivocally good for equity. They expect vehicle prices to fall and anticipate implementation as a shared mobility-as-a-service system. The thinking is that the sharing of the cost of a ride will decrease the marginal cost of a trip and lower the access cost for lower income households. The cost of ownership will be shared between users and the removal of the driving task will drastically lower operating costs relative to taxis. This line of thinking is in contrast with some fundamental principles of economics that I will discuss below.</p>
<p>First, we must consider that this proposed service will have substantial sunk cost research associated with it. Technology development is expensive and we are not looking at a government agency, which will utilize tax revenues to pursue research for public benefit. These are large publically held corporations, with the mandate of maximizing shareholder revenue. Absent of government intervention via subsidies, initial AV trips will be expensive and available to the wealthy. Rudimentary microeconomics states that this is the path of any non-inferior good: consumption will increase with increasing available capital.</p>
<p>I would like to provide an example to structure the argument. Consider a vehicle with capacity for 5 occupants. A firm can choose to 1) charge $1 for each passenger in order to provide a service available to all residents of the city or 2) charge $4 for each passenger, knowing that a large segment of the population will be excluded from the service. In order for case 1 to govern, the firm must be certain of at least 4 passengers for each trip. As a risk averse agent, the firm will invariably decided to charge $4 knowing they only need to capture a single rider for each trip to break even with respect to case 1. Additional passengers will rapidly increase the profits of the firm beyond what could be provided under case 1. This brings us back to the issue of equity and its spatial component. If we assume that there is spatial segregation by income group (a very reasonable assumption), we can say that $4 trips will be concentrated in set of sub-regions within the city. We can consider a situation of $4 “trip signals” for a high income sub-region and $1 “trip signals” from a low income sub-region. The shared mobility operator, seeking to optimize their vehicle routing, will deploy the majority of their vehicles in areas where they can maximize their profits - a function of the demand for trips at the prevailing rate of service.</p>
<p>AV and mobility-as-a-service raise questions about willingness-to-pay and willingness-to-share. Absent government input, these services will act solely based on market forces. Current patterns of auto ownership and usage suggest people would be willing to pay a substantial premium to avoid vehicle sharing. In a culture of 1.20 vehicle occupancies, can we consider shared mobility as a likely outcome? Profit seeking private vehicle operators will have no qualms about circulating vehicles through upper income communities where the highest premium can be gained for each trip. This will exclude lower income households from use of the service. Lower operating costs does not necessarily mean that prices will drop. The price of a trip will be a function of the willingness-to-pay for each person and the number of persons who are willing to pay a given price, that is aggregate demand. It may be the case that operators can maintain sufficient ridership at high prices and not require a lower price to draw in additional ridership. Each vehicle will still constitute a capital cost and firms will seek to maximize unit (vehicle) profit and technology costs will be high for each vehicle.</p>
<p>I do not argue that prices will not come down eventually, but the risk is that during the period of partial AV penetration barriers will form that exclude, or inhibit, the adoption of this new mobility tool by lower income households. Consideration of equity in transportation and land use model forecasts will be critical in informing government policy to mitigate these effects. I have seen the effects of transportation on social exclusion through my travels in South America and even here in Canada and the United States. These considerations will be particularly important in developing cities, where government incentive structures may differ from what we see in North American cities. Work conducted with the PECAS model framework in Caracas, Venezuala has proven the ability of these tools to quantify the equity challenges of transportation policy. We need only examine the locations where AV testing is currently taking place to see the potential inequity in its service provision. Major testing is occuring in Palo Alto and other technology hubs, among Richard Florida’s Creative Class - engineers, software developers, and the like. AV adoption has the potential to alleviate issues of accessibility and inequity of access, but we cannot negate the possibility of it exacerbating these problems in an environment of market-driven mobility.</p>
<p>Some final thoughts on the topic: How will luxury services affect access to AV? There is the potential for segregation of the market and higher quality services made available to those who can afford them. As infrastructure evolves to meet the needs of AV, I question whether this evolution will occur uniformly through the city or be focused in higher income communities where residents have the social capital to influence policy and the financial capital to become early adopters of the technology.</p>
<p><em>Written during my Ph.D.&nbsp;(Nov.&nbsp;30, 2018)…</em> A great source of inspiration in my thinking this past year has been the podcast EconTalk with Russ Roberts. This week Russ spoke with the Political Economist Michael Munger about his new book “Tomorrow 3.0: Transaction Costs and the Sharing Economy” and, more generally, the sharing economy. Their discussion raised some questions for me around my own research in transportation and land use. Michael placed great emphasis on the importance of transaction costs, which include and bear a close resemblance to transportation costs and accessibility. Michael defines transactions costs into three, conveniently ‘t-suffixed’ words, namely: triangulation, transfer, and trust. He gives the case of the Sears catalogue as an early 20th century example of reducing transaction costs. The catalogue provided a medium for the aggregation of a wide variety of goods for sale. The Sears catalogue can be argued to be a predecessor of Amazon. Both represented major leaps forward in our ability to reduce transaction costs. The goods are provided in a centralized location (fulfilling triangulation), low cost in their distribution networks (transfer), and trusted by consumers. The ability to rate suppliers is a key ingredient in the success of Amazon and, focusing on the shared economy, the emergence of software that provides a means of trust in non-traditional market transactions. Consider Uber, which provides a service similar to hitchhiking in its lack of regulation. Users trust the service because Uber acts as an intermediary system of vetting for drivers.</p>
<p>Michael and Russ spend the first portion of the podcast talking about the sharing economy and the cost of durable goods. There are many goods we rarely use (e.g.&nbsp;power tools), which could be rented rather than owned. The main criteria for an effective shared durable good is that it have a high purchase price and low frequency of use. Michael provides an example of autonomous vehicles transporting rented equipment between homes, which is intriguing but also MIGHT presents challenges with respect to road congestion. I say might because it is not straightforward to compare individuals making purchases at the store with a centralized provider of goods, who can potentially optimize their route planning and carry many goods in a single vehicle. There are interesting questions around where the tradeoff lies between the cost of ownership and the cost of rental, including transportation costs.</p>
<p>One point that stood out for me in their discussion was the space requirement for durable goods. The primary examples are cars and large power tools. They discuss how space requirements for dwellings might be reduced by a diminished storage requirement within the home. Mind blown! It is so intuitive, but yet is not something I have considered at length. I am a great hoarder of books, which take up precious shelf space in our small apartment. The library is a (very) old example of the sharing economy in this particular space. I generally take advantage of this resource but the transaction costs are high for the cost of the good: I need to be sure the book is available at my local branch or reserve the book - requiring a wait for the satisfaction of reading a particular book. I’m often rough with my books, adding to my preference for ownership. None the less, it raises interesting questions about the reduction in building footprint associated with the shared ownership of cars, and perhaps other large durable goods.</p>
<p>Michael and Russ talk about Uber being a framework for sharing, well outside the transportation realm. I think this evolution is highly probable and it raises some fascinating questions for transportation and land use researchers. These are fundamentally questions of transportation, accessibility, proximity, and time - in the parlance of my field. It is an exciting time to begin in this field, indeed!</p>
<p>My usual notes on these topics: how will these new technologies affect equity? How can new technologies be framed in the context of networks? This is a topic I am ruminating on as a potential book idea. I have an enormous passion for history, which is largely untapped in my research. I have been thinking a lot about topics for a book that mix my interest in history with the perspective of a Transportation Engineer. We shall see where it leads…</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>technology</category>
  <category>autonomous vehicles</category>
  <category>equity</category>
  <guid>https://UNL-Hawkins-Lab.github.io/Hawkinslab/thoughts/posts/07-03-2017/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 03 Jul 2017 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://UNL-Hawkins-Lab.github.io/Hawkinslab/thoughts/posts/07-03-2017/banner.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
