<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Hawkinslab</title>
<link>https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/blog.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/blog.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.6.39</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 07:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Our Grand Omaha to Calgary Trip</title>
  <dc:creator>Jason Hawkins</dc:creator>
  <link>https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/01-16-2025/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="overview" class="level1">
<h1>Overview</h1>
<p>In 2024, I received an offer to return to Canada and join the faculty at the Univerity of Calgary. My partner and I both did our degrees at the University of Calgary and love western Canada, so we were excited to return. The University very generously covered the cost of our relocation, including both household goods and a good portion of our trip back with our vehicle.</p>
<p>Would I recommend driving a Chevrolet Bolt 2,500 km with two small kids and a trunk full of suitcases and food? It depends on your kids and personal fortitude. My children are amazing roadtrip buddies. You also need to accept that you are not going to get anywhere fast. We spread our trip out over about a week. It also requires a lot of planning, particularly when you are driving through the US Midwest, which is not known for its extensive network of public charging stations. The 2023 Chevrolet Bolt also has a limit of 50kW on its charging rate - lots of fun getting to an ultra fast 350 kW station and maxing out at about 45 kW.</p>
<section id="route" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="route">Route</h2>
<p>Our route was partially determined by the location of charging stations and partially by landmarks along the way. We knew we wanted to see Mount Rushmore and stop at Waterton Lakes National Park when we crossed into Canada.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/01-16-2025/trip-map.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Route map</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="charging" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="charging">Charging</h2>
<p>To understand long-distance travel by EV, one needs a basic knowledge of the charging technology. The Society of Automotive Engineers (SAE) defines three levels, but they vary widely in their power - i.e., speed. Power is simply a measure of how much energy a charger can deliver in a given time. It’s usually measured in kW, or thousands of Joules of energy per second.</p>
<p><strong>Level 1</strong> is the lowest charging level. It’s what you get with a typical 120V outlet. Basically, you are charging your car with the power of a hairdryer. A typical Level 1 charger will deliver about 1.2-2.4 kW, which translates to about 5 km of range per hour of charging. It is slow! We have a Level 1 charger at home, which works fine for our minimal driving needs.</p>
<p><strong>Level 2</strong> is the middle of the road charger that many people install in their homes. It operates at 240V. Keeping the air dryer analogy going, if a Level 1 charger is a hair dryer then Level 2 is a clothing dryer. It’ll give you about 20-52 km of driving range per hour of charging. These are great overnight charging options if you drive a lot, but they are still a bit slow for long-distance trips. However, they’re often cheap (or free) to use and widely available. Campgrounds are also starting to provide Level 2 service through their RV power supply units.</p>
<p><strong>Level 3 or DCFC</strong> is the quickest option. Depending on the station, these can provide 50-500 kW of power. Note that some vehicles (e.g., our Chevrolet Bolt with a limit of 50 kW) cannot make full use of DCFC. Most stations we saw on our drive were 250-350 kW units. DCFC stations will charge most vehicles from empty in about 30-45 minutes, though the time is decreasing and you probably don’t want to arrive at a station with less than 20 percent charge.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="day-1-omaha-ne-to-sioux-falls-sd" class="level1">
<h1>Day 1: Omaha, NE to Sioux Falls, SD</h1>
<p>Our first day was a hectic. The movers arrived in the morning and we needed to be in Sioux Falls, SD by that evening to be on track. Unfortunately, the movers were not the best planners. They ran out of boxes midday and we had to wait around for several hours for a resupply. With a plan to be out of town by 3PM at the latest, we left Omaha at 4PM after cleaning up their mess around the house.</p>
<p>The drive from Omaha to Sioux Falls was fairly uneventful. We passed through Iowa and arrived after dark. We left Omaha with 90% charge and arrived at our hotel with 25% charge. The first night was a series of hard lessons though. Public charging stations remain a <em>wild west</em>. You need half a dozen different apps on your phone to be ready to charge at any station along your route. On the topic of charging, <strong>make sure your phone is charged!</strong> Navigating to a charging station in the dark and rain with minimal vehicle charge <strong>and</strong> a phone on its last bit of juice is not a good combination. I used a DCFC managed by EV Connect on the other side of town from our hotel. We went back and forth by text message, with me at the charging station and my partner at the hotel with the kids, trying to sort out how to start the session when she had the EV Connect app on her phone (we had to split the apps between our phones because neither of us had sufficient space to install all the apps on our phone and maintain space for photos along the route).</p>
<p>Once we sorted out the charging logististics, it was a nice experience. I sat in an auto dealership parking lot and listened to the radio - again, no phone charge. It was the week of the Democratic National Convention and the Obamas were center stage that night. What a one-two punch of speeches! Unfortunately, as we now know in hindsight, my family was on the run from a spray tanned geriatric who would throw Canada into tarriff threat-induced chaos. At the time, we fell peacefully fast asleep after a very long first day of travel home.</p>
</section>
<section id="day-2-sioux-falls-sd-to-rapid-city-sd" class="level1">
<h1>Day 2: Sioux Falls, SD to Rapid City, SD</h1>
<p>We stayed in Sioux Falls for a bit the next morning. After charging the previous night, we had an 81% charge and wanted to get a bit more range before leaving town for a full day of driving. We explored the riverfront and walked to the eponymous falls, while our car got a slowish charge from a Level 2 ChargePoint station. The falls did not disappoint. For context, we lived in Toronto during my Ph.D., so Niagara Falls was a weekend trip. That is to say, the falls are an impressive sight even for Canadians accustomed to great natural wonders. They are a swirling and bubbling mass, with massive red-brown rocky outcroppings.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/01-16-2025/IMG_20240821_080222366_HDR.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Charger</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>As I said, they are impressive falls and well worth a visit if you are in the area.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/01-16-2025/IMG_20240821_082710772_HDR.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Falls</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Walking through downtown afterwards, I got the feeling that the city took advantage of its local resources as many buildings are built of the same stone.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/01-16-2025/IMG_20240821_084540966_HDR.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Sioux Falls Building</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>A common thread in our drive across South Dakota was the many signs for Wall Drugs. The signs actually started the previous day on I-29 driving north through Iowa, but we didn’t start recording them until the second day. It was a classic midcontinental roadtrip experience. There isn’t much civilization or reason to stop, so businesses work very hard to draw you in. Wall Drugs is the best I have seen. It seemed every sign had a new attration available for your viewing pleasure - food, coffee, a splashpad, dinosaurs, and a petting zoo (I made the last one up because I couldn’t recall all the attractions. I had to confirm online there isn’t one because it would not surprise me to find out they have the second largest zoo in the region, after Omaha.). A small drug store, purchased in 1931 by Ted Hustead and expanded into a 76,000 square foot tourist attraction on the way to Mount Rushmore. We aren’t big fans of trinkets and tchotchke so didn’t stay long, but if that is your scene then all power to you and enjoy the wonders of Wall Drugs!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/01-16-2025/IMG_20240821_093857479_HDR.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Walls Drugs</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/01-16-2025/IMG_20240821_094755704.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Walls Drugs</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>We stopped to charge in Mitchell, SD and I took a meeting by Zoom.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/01-16-2025/IMG_20240821_102839285_HDR.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Charger</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>We stopped again in Chamberlain, SD to charge and went to Subway. We didn’t get a good picture of it, but the hill to Missouri River is quite impressive. Don’t believe the stories that there is no topography in the Midwest. It’s there if you look for it.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/01-16-2025/IMG_20240821_125804423_HDR.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Charger</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Wall drugs!!!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/01-16-2025/IMG_20240821_135709140.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Walls Drugs</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Don’t forget… stop at Wall Drugs for their many attractions.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/01-16-2025/IMG_20240821_141722421.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Walls Drugs</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Don’t just see wall drugs - go to the Firehouse Brewery in Rapid City. Though their advertising campaign was slightly less extensive, the Firehouse Brewery also has quite a few fun signs along I-90.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/01-16-2025/IMG_20240821_141746252.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Brewery</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>We went back and forth with this truck all day. It looked like they were transporting a wind turbine tower (or a section of a NASA rocket).</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/01-16-2025/IMG_20240821_145635153_HDR.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Truck</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>My partner and I had heard mixed reviews about Mount Rushmore. Some people said that it is not as big as you expect. We mostly knew it from Hitchcock’s North by Northwest. It is a nice drive through the Black Hills to the entrance road, though steep and winding so make sure you have plenty of charge. The National Park Service has a smooth operation - parking attendants and a large concrete parkade rising out of the forest. First, thank you for the free charging stations at the monument. Second, Mount Rushmore is an impressive sight. We spend some time at the monument and had lunch at the cafe - standard hot dogs and hamburgers.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/01-16-2025/IMG_20240821_174714502.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Rushmore</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>We did not have a charging station at our hotel in Rapid City, but there was a Level 2 charger at the office of the local utility (Black Hills Electric) across the street - i.e., across the freeway. It was well maintained and available upon arrival.</p>
</section>
<section id="day-3-rapid-city-sd-to-billings-mt" class="level1">
<h1>Day 3: Rapid City, SD to Billings, MT</h1>
<p>The next day, we left for Montana via Wyoming with a 100% charge. Our route was slightly altered by the ubiqituous wildfires of summer, so we were happy to have a full charge.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/01-16-2025/IMG_20240822_082335349_HDR.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Wyoming sign</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>We stopped in Gillette, WY to charge and get some groceries. We also re-planned our route to bypass the wildfires on I-90 near Buffallo, WY.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/01-16-2025/IMG_20240822_102557399_HDR.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Charger</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I’ll pause to note the changing landscapes on a long-distance trip. We passed through prairie and badlands, mountains and dunes. While long-distance drives inevitably have their moments of monotony, it is hard not to be struck by the beauty and diversity of this planet. As a civil engineer, I noticed another type of beauty - the many hews of pavement as local mineral compositions changed over our drive. Greys, changed to reds, then blacks as we traversed South Dakota and Wyoming. It is a reminder of how the uniformity and standards of engineering cannot overcome natural diversity.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/01-16-2025/IMG_20240822_104312292_HDR.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Landscape</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Having made it safely past the wildfires, we were relieved to stop in Sheridan, WY for a charge and a surprisingly nice lunch from the local gas station.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/01-16-2025/IMG_20240822_123905524_HDR.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Charger</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Unpictured: we stopped at the Target upon arrival in Billings, MT to charge for the night because our hotel did not have a nearby charging option. We also went for dinner and continued our charging session at a nearby parkade.</p>
</section>
<section id="day-4-billings-mt-to-grand-falls-mt" class="level1">
<h1>Day 4: Billings, MT to Grand Falls, MT</h1>
<p>From Billings, we drove north and stopped at a playground in Harlowton, MT for some decompression and charging. There were no public charging stations through this section of our trip. Fortunately, a campground offered charging at their RV plugins (220V - Level 2) for a $5 fee.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/01-16-2025/IMG_20240823_130147196.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Charger</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>We had a lovely drive through the rolling hills of Montana leading to our final US stop - Great Falls, MT. Our hotel had a Level 2 charger and we had a nice evening in the rain.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/01-16-2025/IMG_20240823_160248399.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Charger</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="day-5-great-falls-mt-to-waterton-lakes-ab" class="level1">
<h1>Day 5: Great Falls, MT to Waterton Lakes, AB</h1>
<p>We were relieved to cross the Sweetwater, MT-Coutts, AB border crosing into Canada! The change was fairly immediate. We stopped at a flo station in Milk River, AB. It was a DCFC sponsored by ATCO Gas a consortium of regional and federal government agencies.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/01-16-2025/IMG_20240824_122244992_HDR.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Charger</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I decided to take a picture of the instructions and sponsor text. Note the clear charging instructions, wayfinding map, and “Kumbaya” collaboration of various groups to make a network happen. As the saying goes, “we are not in Kansas (Nebraska) anymore”. I remain hopeful that Canada will not lose this culture of collaboration in the wilderness, but we will see how various events turn out over the coming months.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/01-16-2025/IMG_20240824_122254856.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Charger</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>We had a great view from this charger in Waterton Lakes, AB. Unfornately, I made the mistake of leaving our vehicle parked overnight and paying the parking charge after reaching 100% charge. My partner and I have fond memories of visiting Waterton Lakes pre-children when we were dating and living together in Calgary. We took our kids around the park to re-create various memories because we are cheesy people.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/01-16-2025/IMG_20240824_145938456_HDR.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Charger</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="day-6-waterton-lakes-ab" class="level1">
<h1>Day 6: Waterton Lakes, AB</h1>
<p>Did I mention how great it felt to be home in Canada! We spent a couple days at the park relaxing after our long drive north.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/01-16-2025/IMG_20240825_102600747_HDR.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Landscape</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="day-7-waterton-lakes-ab-to-calgary-ab" class="level1">
<h1>Day 7: Waterton Lakes, AB to Calgary, AB</h1>
<p>After some much needed relaxation, we continued our journal north to Calgary. What better way to return home than a trip to IKEA. Nebraska has no IKEA store, partially because Warren Buffett’s Nebraska Furniture Mart is a local substitute. NFM is great, but we did miss our Swedish meatballs and lingonberry drink. The many charging stations (both free and paid), as well as free daycare, make IKEA a great destination for the EV-owning family. Disclaimer: I work for the University of Calgary and am not paid by IKEA. I just really like the place.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/01-16-2025/IMG_20240826_155500948_HDR.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Charger</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>travel</category>
  <category>infrastructure</category>
  <guid>https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/01-16-2025/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/01-16-2025/banner.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Technology and Development</title>
  <dc:creator>Jason Hawkins</dc:creator>
  <link>https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/10-29-2024/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>I’ll return to our old friend Schumacher today, but with a different focus and more recent insights from Acemoglu and Johnson (2024 winners of The Sveriges Riksbank Prize in Economic Sciences in Memory of Alfred Nobel, along with James A. Robinson). The topic for today is what Schumacher terms <em>intermediate technology</em> in the context of development economics. The problem to be addressed is the uplift of economic and living conditions for those living in developing nations, principally those outside major cities – i.e., in villages and small towns. An important factor for these residents is the lack of financial and institutional supports for industrial development using the same technology as employed in developed nations. Schumacher identifies a negative effect on employment if development focuses solely on industrial enterprise in major cities, which he sees as leading to the “migration of destitute people into towns that cannot absorb them” (SIB, p.&nbsp;183). While I have a rosier perspective than that of Schumacher (he was not a fan of cities as a general rule), I agree with his notion that maximizing output per person will not be as effective as maximizing the available work opportunities. Schumacher calls this principle <em>intermediate technology</em> for its focus on providing an intermediate technological solution – one that improves working conditions beyond their current levels but does not automate production to the point of eliminating low skill labour. Without an extensive tangent, the term <em>low skill</em> (or <em>unskilled</em>) has always bothered me. It seems a snobbish way of describing skilled labour obtained over many years of practice, though perhaps not in a formal educational setting. It is also the case the agricultural work in the developed world (again, a bit of an imprecise term) requires much formal education in agricultural science, mechanical engineering, and other fields.</p>
<p>Schumacher makes it clear that modern industry cannot meet the needs of developing nations, which are rich in labour and short on capital, given that the processes are tailored to nations short on labour and rich in capital. He defines an intermediate technology using the reference of developing nation technology as a $1 technology and developed nation technology as a $1000 technology. What is needed is a $100 technology, one which improves the efficiency of production without a significant reduction in labour requirements and at a capital cost. Without restating Schumacher verbatim, we can consider two ways of approaching intermediate technology: 1) a small-scale deployment of a current technology. He gives the example of a small-scale petroleum refinery that has a lower capital cost but with similar levels of efficiency of their larger counterparts; 2) the use of a technology from the recent past, during a time when developed nations relied more heavily on labour rather than capital. A couple scenarios I have observed in my own life ring true with the approach of Schumacher. As a high school student, I had the opportunity to travel to the Peruvian Andes on a school trip. We worked with a local village to construct a preschool. One of the key features of the construction that I recall was the use of local materials. Having heard of other projects using modern materials (e.g., a steel roof, plywood walls, etc.) leading to issues for the community when the structured failed or required repairs, I thought the use of local materials was an excellent idea. While it did not result in a shiny modern building, the school fit into the context of the village and employed methods and materials known to the residents. I was also reminded of a program a friend took part in during our time as undergraduate students. She worked with an NGO to repair medical equipment in a central American hospital (I believe it was in Guatemala). The hospital received donations of medical equipment, but it often lacked the local expertise to make repairs to the equipment. This case reminds me of the way transit management often works, with government being excited about a new train line but more apathetic about operations and maintenance.</p>
<p>Let me turn now to the work of Acemoglu and Johnson. In their book “Power and Progress”, they provide an interesting analysis of technology and its relationship with prosperity. A motivation for their work is the effect of artificial intelligence on progress and its equitable distribution. They highlight the cases of South Korea, Taiwan, Mauritius, and China as seeing rapid growth (of greater than 5 percent per year) due to their integration into the technology economy, in conjunction with exports to global markets. Acemoglu and Johnson provide examples that parallel the arguments of Schumacher, though they do not reference his work. For example, high- and middle-income nations invest heavily in research into crop pest and pathogen solutions. Corn strains resistant to the European Maize Borer and Western Corn Rootworm have been developed over the last few decades. However, most of these crop strains and chemicals are not useful to African or Asian farmers facing infestations of African Maize Stalk Borer or Desert Locust. They cite estimates that global agricultural productivity could be raised by 42 percent if research was redirected towards pests and pathogens affecting crops in low-income nations. They also highlight the negative effects on equality associated with capital-intensive solutions adopted from high-income nations in development work. Such solutions lead to a small and well-paid workforce operating alongside a larger and low paid workforce using existing capital.</p>
<p>We now come to a central thesis of Acemoglu and Johnson that the AI revolution risks producing an economy that replaces low-skilled labour without a viable alternative outlet for that labour. AI requires highly skilled production and service labour, resources severely lacking in most developing nations. A key point here is that technology should raise the marginal productivity of labour, not replace it. Such a pattern was associated with the Industrial Revolution of the 18th century. Development began with the power in the hands of a small number of capital owners, before shifting to workers through changes in social power. Acemoglu and Johnson chart this history over 1000 years and make the argument that AI is not following the same path of facilitating marginal labour productivity growth and distribution of social power to the population. They advocate for machine usefulness over machine intelligence. It is an interesting discussion, but one that goes beyond the scope of this article.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>development economics</category>
  <guid>https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/10-29-2024/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 29 Oct 2024 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/10-29-2024/banner.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Travel Behaviour as Scientific Art</title>
  <dc:creator>Jason Hawkins</dc:creator>
  <link>https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/07-30-2024/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>When I was a child, my parents would read poetry to me. Statistically speaking, I don’t know the percent of engineering professors with this particular life experience, but I would hazard to guess it is small. One of my favourite poems was Robert Frost’s “The Road Not Taken”. The message I got from it was to pursue the path not taken, which I’d like to think I have taken forward in my life. I recently read Thomas Kuhn’s “The Structure of Scientific Revolutions”, one of those books that people like to say they read to sound intellectual but only skim a few pages then read the Wikipedia page - I read about 80% before skimming.</p>
<p>One of the key insights by Kuhn is that science differs from other fields in its linear treatment of innovation. That is, a scientific field reaches a divergence in the yellow wood and takes a single path. Kuhn characterizes the evolution of science in terms of general science and paradigm shifts. General science is the drudgery of research to make incremental advancements. Paradigm shifts are rare but move a field in a new direction. The key difference from other fields, at least according to Kuhn, is that the shift means a releasing of past ideas. After Einstein developed general relativity, Newtonian gravitation was deemed incomplete and a previous paradigm. While there may be a certain amount of competition among theories at a given time, there will ultimately be a winner.</p>
<p>I think Kuhn is making an interesting insight, but I would also argue it’s largely a feature of fundamental physical sciences. To clarify his point, we can consider visual art. Cubism and Art Deco developed during the same period, but one did not subsume the other after vigorous discussion among artists. In art, multiple schools of thought can exist without raising questions of consistency. There are certainly debates about the merits of style and individuals are free to express their opinion about a particular piece of art, but revolution does not invalidate the continued pursuit of extent styles.</p>
<p>In my own field of travel behaviour, we often talk about modeling human behaviour as a mix of science and art. I think this rings true in the Kuhnian sense that parallel theories or approaches can coexist without being incongruent. When two roads diverge in the woods of behaviour, there is merit to pursuing both paths in order to get a fuller picture of behaviour. To come full circle, I recently read “Cosmic Wonder” by the young Canadian astronomer (from Victoria, BC - yes, my parents got me a signed copy) Nathan Hellner-Mestelman. It brought me back to my high school days reading pop science cosmology by Brian Greene and others. While I think Kuhn made some deep insights, I think physical sciences can also overstate its knowledge of the universe. They should also feel the freedom to pursue diverse paths, even if it diverges from the conventional wisdom and never leads to a paradigm shift. Of course, questions of consistency and equilibrium of thought (i.e., you cannot build on a scattered foundation) are important. We just need to not take ourselves too seriously as scientists and recognize we are all really artists - even if our fourth grade teacher told us we were no good at art.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>philosophy of science</category>
  <category>metascience</category>
  <category>roads in woods</category>
  <guid>https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/07-30-2024/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jul 2024 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/07-30-2024/banner.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Schumacher On Development</title>
  <dc:creator>Jason Hawkins</dc:creator>
  <link>https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/07-12-2024/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>p.&nbsp;173 of SIB</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>development</category>
  <category>intermediate technology</category>
  <guid>https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/07-12-2024/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jul 2024 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/07-12-2024/banner.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Computing The Climate</title>
  <dc:creator>Jason Hawkins</dc:creator>
  <link>https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/07-01-2024/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Happy Canada Day!</p>
<p>As a member of the <a href="https://zephyrtransport.org/">Zephyr Foundation</a>, I spend a fair bit of time thinking about transportation analysis and how to make it more open and transparent. At the same time, I am an academic who conducts computational research and thinks about how to do a better job of sharing data, code, and papers. On the paper front, I do an okay job. On the data and code… it’s a work in progress. A few years ago (Joe Castiglione tells me it was maybe 2015), there was a session at the Transportation Research Board (TRB) annual meeting on hurrican forecasting and how they collaborate on model development. The implication is that we as transportation modelers could follow a similar path to more collaborative and transparent model practices. My perspective on this question comes from experience in local government, consulting, and academia. I think there are two difference between hurricane and transportation demand forecasting that are relevant to this discussion (likely many more, but let’s focus on two avoid a classic Hawkins multi-dimensional ramble).</p>
<p>The first difference is the spatial scope. Transportation demand models tend to be developed at the metropolitan or state scale. The reason this matters is that it has led to a competitive market among consulting firms. While a hurricane forecast model is essentially a natural monopoly - i.e., there is a large region affected and competing commercial models would not be feasible as only one contract would be awarded by a federal agency. Granted, there are competing research models for hurricans, which we do not tend to see in transportation where competition occurs among firms but across metropolitan areas (minimal comparison of models within a single region). Consider the excellent <a href="https://mitpress.mit.edu/9780262048101/forecasting-travel-in-urban-america/">history of the transportation forecasting field in the United States</a> by Konstantinos Chatzis. While including many prominent academics, it is predominantly a history of consultancy and commercial contracts rather than academic grants to develop general model systems (with the except of TRANSIMS, POLARIS, and a few other example) - note: while I love the POLARIS developers, it is still a largely commercial package in that model applications rely on grant dollars for development within a specific region and the codebase is not wholely available open access.</p>
<p>The second difference is the politics of transportation. I am not an expert on hurricanes and disaster management, but I think we can be fairly confident politics has less influence on the location of hurricanes (at the risk of a digression - politics certainly has some indirect effect on the frequency and severity of hurricanes through insufficient action on anthropogenic climate change). Transportation investments are an extremely politic process, particuarly at the scale assessed by transportation demand models. These politics lead to distorted incentives, legal battles, and other messiness.</p>
<p>Related to hurricane forecasting, climate models seek to forecast climatic conditions in response to technology and policy decisions, as well as economic and health impacts depending upon the particular model focus. Steve Easterbrook at the University of Toronto provides an excellent overview of this field in <a href="https://www.environment.utoronto.ca/people/directories/all-faculty/steve-easterbrook">Computing The Climate</a>. I’ve yet to shell out for the full book, but the Chapter 1, 2, and 9 are available online. The book is highly readable, including a nice history and summary of interviews with modeling teams from around the world. As stated by Steve: &gt; The question they were called upon to answer wasn’t whether the planet would warm in response to rising carbon dioxide emissions – by the late 1970s, that was no longer in dispute in the scientific community. The question was: how certain can we be about the numbers?</p>
<p>Hey, this sounds a lot like the uncertainty movement in transportation demand modeling! We’re just 50 years late to the game. One impetus for these efforts to understand climate uncertainty was a report from the JASON group (a group of top physicist advisors to the US president on nuclear security matters. They were named for Jason and the Argonauts - I wasn’t part of the team, being born many years after its inception). National Academy of Science (NAS) panels were established and many discussions had as to how best to model climate systems and quantify uncertainty. While NAS has empaneled many committees on transportation issues, to my understand they have not had the same collectivizing effect on our field.</p>
<p>One reason I like Steve’s book is that he is not a climate scientist. He is a computer scientist interested in how large teams of scientists, largely untrained in production grade software development practices, develop complex computer programs and manage quality control. This topic is generalizable and very useful to understand! Something I found interesting from the start was the MetOffice approach in the UK. Their climate model is built on the same code base as the weather model. The weather model must be run daily to provide forecasts to the UK government and public. As such, its code is constantly reviewed, optimized, and validated against observations. This software setup means the climate model code also exhibits a high level of consistency. The parallel I could draw to transportation is that we produce daily road condition reports, short-term forecasts at intersections, Waze routing recommendations, etc. However, these models are decentralized and variable. They are not a national forecast produced by one centralized agency. Within a metropolitan area, I could see a structure similar to that of the MetOffice being feasible. We have loads of new data and model providers - StreetLight, INRIX, Replica, etc. - which could be ingested into a short-term forecasting and analysis software framework. That same forecasting framework could be extended to provide long-range forecasts at greater spatial aggregation and with additional modules for auto ownership and other long-term decisions. It’s not a perfectly fleshed out idea, but it is something.</p>
<p><strong>Charney Sensitivity</strong> - You’ll have to read Steve’s book to get the full history, but Jules Charney was an early climate modeler - as in was tasked by John von Neumann in 1948 to build a weather forecasting program. The concept of Charney Sensitivity is simple. Double the <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?CO_2"> in the atmosphere and see what happens a few decades in the future. Do models agree? The first issue we would face in transportation modeling is that not all models follow an evolutionary, path dependent, simulation approach. Many models forecast population, land use, economics, and transportation with separate and loosely coupled model systems. Furthermore, many of these models simply provide forecasts for a subset of future years (say 10, 25, 40 years into the future). It could be difficult to compare these models. One “elephant in the room” referenced above is that most models are developed by consultants. Backcasting to check the accuracy of a model or comparing your model against the competitor models may not be good for business. However, we can take a different perspective, as was done by Charney and his team when tasked with the problem of uncertainty quantification by US President Jimmy Carter in the 1970s. While each model may provide a single output that will vary as a function of slight differences in model formulation and setup, the combination of results provides an uncertainty band on the climate (transportation) future.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>climate modeling</category>
  <guid>https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/07-01-2024/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2024 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/07-01-2024/banner.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Emergy and States</title>
  <dc:creator>Jason Hawkins</dc:creator>
  <link>https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/06-24-2024/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Howard T. Odum was an American ecologist and systems theorist. He developed the principles of emergy beginning in the 1950s in response to an inadequate representation of the <em>quality</em> variation among various forms of energy. Emergy is defined as the amount of energy consumed in direct and indirect transformations for the production of a product or service. Its standard unit is the emjoule, measured in a consistent form of energy (typically solar energy). Emergy is then a measure of the amount of solar energy required to produce a particular energy source.</p>
<p>I found the concept a bit opaque based on the Wikipedia page. The International Association for the Advacement of Emergy provides a nice example that helped me understand the idea. Consider a log. The available energy in the log is the heat it can provided through the process of its combustion. Its emergy is measured as the required input energy through sunlight and transpiration to grow the tree, harvest the tree, and process that tree into a log (and other contributions for it to reach your home). We can think of emergy as an input measurement equivalent to the energy output we typically consider in analysis. The objective inherent in emergy is to provide a consistent comparison between the usefulness of different products or services, as well as their energy efficiency. For example, the energy in a log measured in Joules is not readily comparable to that embodied in human metabolism because they do not produce comparable outputs (heating in the case of a log and heat, movement, and various other outputs in the case of human metabolism). Emergy lets us consider the inputs in a common unit based on the required solar energy.</p>
<p>A nice metric we can derive from emergy is <em>transformity</em>, measured as the remaining energy in the product compared with its input energy - measured in se/J. From the second law of thermodynamics, we know that available energy decreases with each transformation. However, the emergy at the start of the process will remain fixed. As a result, the transformity (se/J) of the remaining available energy tends to increase with each transformation - more emergy is required per unit of energy. This makes sense to me if we consider progressive steps down the line. For example, the emergy required for a unit of human metabolism will be a function of the conversion rate of food energy into human energy; food production will require some energy from fertilizers, water, transportation, etc.; each of these products will require some amount of energy from electricity, sunlight, etc.; and so on. A given quantity of energy produced via human metabolism will require a greater input of solar energy (emergy) than a similar quantity of energy for fertilizer, as there are energy loses along the intermediate steps and inputs to human metabolism that are separate from its fertilizer requirements.</p>
<p>Another concept I’d like to write about today is the steady state economy. The idea here is that an economy can be defined that is constant in its population and capital stocks. I was reminded of this concept while reviewing a chapter of the Nebraska Climate Plan today. They discussed the idea of “sustainable growth”. By including the term “growth”, the discussion is already framed in a context of non-steady state sustainability. If we consider the IPAT equation (Impact = Population x Affluence x Technology), “sustainable growth” requires that technology play an inordinate role to ensure stable, or preferably declining impacts, because neither population nor affluence are held at steady state conditions. The growth mindset is unfortunately baked into many analyses. We see it in IEA/EIA forecasts - not just growing population but growth of the “good things” (renewables, electric vehicles, energy efficiency, etc.) into the future. The only variation is by how much these various quantities are assumed to grow. Even the paragon of capitalist economics, Adam Smith, believed national economies would reach stationary conditions. Herman Daly, a prominent ecological economists, argued for a steady state economy, based on natural resource flows, that would impose hard limits on resource use. This view differs from the classical view beginning with Smith, which believed that conditions would evolve without government intervention. While Daly’s approach seems restrictive and infeasible in a democratic society, I also believe it naive to assume that stationarity will naturally evolve as a function of standard market evolution. In my work, I am starting to examining these views from a microeconomic perspective through econometric model estimation. While not a perfect solution to the forecasting problem inherent in the discussion, this approach does allow us to operationalize various steady state mechanisms as simulations based upon empirical data and structural behavioural assumptions.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>emergy</category>
  <category>state-state economics</category>
  <category>constraints on growth</category>
  <guid>https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/06-24-2024/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2024 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/06-24-2024/banner.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Schumacher On Scale</title>
  <dc:creator>Jason Hawkins</dc:creator>
  <link>https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/06-10-2024/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>“In the current vocabulary of condemnation there are few words as final and conclusive as the word ‘uneconomic’” (SIB, p.&nbsp;44). Thus states Schumacher in his work “Small is Beautiful” (1973). I believe this pattern still holds true, as does Schumacher’s question as to the “meaning” produced by the methods of economics. Economics does not, and cannot, produce any other meaning aside from adequate profit. While such an assessment would be deemed incorrect by nearly all practicing economists - i.e., other forms of value can be translated into monetary terms, thus obviating the need for ethics, religion, and other forms of value generation. Social, aesthetic, moral, or political reasons need not apply. Robert F. Kennedy demonstrated agreement with the sentiment of Schumacher when, in an address to the University of Kansas on March 18, 1968, he stated “too much and for too long, we seemed to have surrendered personal excellence and community values in the mere accumulation of material things”. Of course, if pressed on the matter, Kennedy might have demurred towards such a philosophy being a nice idea but impractical in the context of a Presidential administration.</p>
<p>I also agree with Schumacher that cost/benefit analysis, while designed to account for costs and benefits that might otherwise go overlooked, tends to reduce the higher to the level of the lower and give a price to that which is priceless. I was particularly struck in my reading of Small Is Beatiful by the notion of “meta-economics”. That is, a bounding of the applicability of economics. Economics deals with the production of man within his/her environment. Meta-economics must then have two parts defined by (1) the study of man and (2) the study of the environment. The lack of understanding of this nature of the field makes for an economic calculus that is ignorant of the reliance of man on the natural world. Schumacher further distinguishes between primary goods (i.e., non-renewable and renewable resources) and secondary goods (i.e., manufactured goods and services). While economics often talks about “production”, Schumacher notes that we are converters only and lack the ability to produce primary goods.</p>
<p>Schumacher turns to the topic of scale through a discussion of a Buddhist-based economic system as a contrast to Western materialism. Schumacher was not a Buddhist. In fact, he was largely irreligious. Buddhism is simply used as one value system (among many) as a basis for an alternative meta-economics. Let us begin with the notion of work. Economics defines work as a disutlity, to me minimized or removed through the application of technology. The Buddhist perspective provides a threefold motivation for labour. First, it is a means to utilize and develop skills. Second, to ovecome the ego by joining with other people in a common task. Third, to produce the goods and services necessary for a fulfilled life. By this viewpoint, work and leisure are equally important and complementary aspects of life. We now come to the question of scale. To the modern economist, standard of living is measured by the amount of consumption. To a Buddhist economist, such a perspective is irrational! Schumacher gives the excellent example of clothing. If the purpose of clothing is to regulate temperature and provide modesty, then the objective will be to provide these outcomes with the minimal input of labour and materials. “It would be highly uneconomic, for instance, to go in for complicated tailoring like the modern West, when a much more beautiful effect can be achieved by the skilful draping of uncut material” (SIB, p.&nbsp;61).</p>
<p>Schumacher argues that scaling and agglomeration dominate, not only modern economic thought, but any number of other fields. He spends some time talking about the appropriate size of a city, setting an upper limit of 500,000 inhabitants. This topic may be one that Schumacher and I differ, at least on the surface. I am a great lover of cities. It is hard not to appreciate large infrastructure as a trained civil engineer. However, I believe Schumacher and I may be in agreement that large scale settlement is only successful when decomposable into smaller units. Having spent time in Toronto as a graduate student, a metropolitan region of far more than 500,000, I believe its success comes from its ability to be decomposed into smaller spatial and social units. This principle relates to the in-vogue concept of the 15-minute city. A mostly self-contained community in terms of access to services is ideal. It is when we scale economic provisioning, such as retail provided at centralized “Big Box Stores”, that the hazards of scale manifest as long and congested travel times. Likewise, recent writings on the benefits of local governance and the power of mayors align well with Schumacher’s downscaling of governance to the community scale. Schumacher advocates for a refocusing of policy on people over goods and profit - “production by the masses, rather than mass production” (SIB, p.&nbsp;79). This is a movement that I can get behind sitting in my basement writing for an audience of one simply because I enjoy the work.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>society</category>
  <category>scale</category>
  <category>buddhist economics</category>
  <guid>https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/06-10-2024/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jun 2024 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/06-10-2024/banner.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Socialist Calculation Debate</title>
  <dc:creator>Jason Hawkins</dc:creator>
  <link>https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/06-06-2024/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>I once had a student call me a socialist for discussing equity in a transportation engineering course. While somewhat humourous and avoiding any tangential discussions on the topic of transportation equity (Cole’s notes: engineers <strong>definitely</strong> need to consider it), they were not wrong that my beliefs on many topics tend towards Democratic Socialism. What I would like to discuss today is Socialist Calculation Debate.</p>
<p>The Socialist Calculation Debate was a debate among economists, beginning in the 1920s, in response to the rise of socialism in Eastern Europe. Von Mises and Hayek argued that socialism was not feasible because it lacked an appropriate means of economic valuation - the law of value. While often framed as a debate between capitalist and socialist economic systems, the debate included internal differences among socialist economists as to the use of markets and money.</p>
<p>This debate interests me in the context of my work on the valuation of ecosystem services. I do not go so far as to say that markets have no value. Within the traditional economic market, price signals are an effective structural mechanism. The issue comes when we extend a system of values developed within the market economy to the wider environment. For a start, we are more than cogs in an economic machine. Thus, our systems of valuation must be more than those employed by the economic market. How to measure value beyond money is certainly a germane question. So how should we do it? I do not have a clear answer. I do not believe this is by definition a statement that we should not pursue answers! In fact, as argued by Thomas Kuhn, it is not always through incremental progress that we achieve innovation. Rather, we must seek out new ways of thinking and analysis. I increasingly find my lack of formal training in economics an asset in that I am unimpeded by a linear training on the subject, to the great consternation of all my economic committee members as a student (“but those aren’t the correct papers to reference!”).</p>
<p>Value theory is the ethical study of how, why, and to what degree we values things. Ecological econmics distinguishes two types of value: donor-type and receiver-type value. We can think of these value types in terms of physical flow accounting. Donor-type value parallels the attribution of physical flows to their point of production (i.e., resource extraction). Receiver-type value parallels the attribution of physical flows to their points of consumption (i.e., households). Odum uses the term <em>emergy</em> to described the embodied energy required for provision of a good or service. Emergy is typically measured in sun energy equivalents - i.e., the sun energy required to produce a fuel, good, or human service. It provides a measure of the <em>quality</em> of energy with respect to their ability to support receiver-type value. As an alternative to monetary value, emergy has many appeals features for the engineering trained in thermodynamics. It does not introduce any artificial distortions of value induced by market fluctuations or rent seeking behaviour.</p>
<p>We can also distinguish between <em>instrumental</em> and <em>intrinsic</em> value, as described by Plato in the Republic. An instrumentally valuable good is one that has value for its provisioning of other valued goods or services - i.e., what a transportation might call a <em>derived demand</em> good. Intrinsically valuable goods have value in their use. The two are not mutually exclusive. In environmental ethics, we can consider the instrumental value of resources for humans, such as the value of forests for their provision of timber used in dwellings. However, forests also have an intrinsic value in their direct provision of beauty. Environmental economics would seek to weigh the tradeoffs between these values - i.e., is the loss of the <em>intrinsic</em> beauty of a forest by cutting down a tree balanced by its <em>instrumental</em> value as an input to economic production. The issue that arises here is that instrumental value is quite easy to quantify in an economic value system. We can simply measure the direct economic benefits. However, intrinsic value is a bit <em>squishier</em> to use the technical term. Does removing a single tree affect the ascetics? What about single stand of trees? Are there ecological impacts from discontinuity in habitats that will affect the intrinsic value of adjecent remaining forested areas? How much is nature beauty worth to us?</p>
<p>At this time, I would like to thank my family for reading these ramblings. I assume no one else will see them aside from a few of my students with the misfortune to click on the wrong page on our research website.</p>
<p>As an aside, the raised fist image has a long history as a social symbol. Extent examples include a painting by Honor'e Daumier from the 1848 French Revolution. On a visit to the Smithsonian Museum of African American History and Culture, I was struck by a group of young African American students posed by a statue commemorating the 1968 Olympics Black Power salute. On the topic of value, it is interesting to observe the shifting patterns and values of a symbol change over time as they are adapted by different groups.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>socialist economics</category>
  <category>value theory</category>
  <guid>https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/06-06-2024/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 06 Jun 2024 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/06-06-2024/banner.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Schumacher On Prediction</title>
  <dc:creator>Jason Hawkins</dc:creator>
  <link>https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/05-28-2024/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Best known for his work on small-scale economics, in the same work (Small is Beautiful), E.F. Schumacher provides one of the best discussions on prediction that I have seen to date. It is also an excellent example of <em>semantics</em> applied in its true sense, rather than the typical pejorative meaning associated with the term in many discussions.</p>
<p>Schumacher distinguishes prediction along three dimensions using a set of <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?2%5E3%20=%208"> cases as follows:</p>
<div class="columns">
<div class="column" style="width:50%;">
<ol type="1">
<li>Act Past Certain</li>
<li>Act Future Certain</li>
<li>Act Past Uncertain</li>
<li>Act Future Uncertain</li>
</ol>
</div><div class="column" style="width:50%;">
<ol start="5" type="1">
<li>Event Past Certain</li>
<li>Event Future Certain</li>
<li>Event Past Uncertain</li>
<li>Event Future Uncertain</li>
</ol>
</div>
</div>
<p>Let us first discuss <em>acts</em> and <em>events</em>. The first (acts) are active and “within the control of the planner”, while the second (events) are passive and “outside the control of the planner”. The planner may be able to forecast events and their influence on plans, but they cannot be part of the plans. <em>Plan</em> and <em>estimate</em>, while appearing to apply to the future only, are often applied to past events. For example, “I shall not visit Paris without a plan” can mean “I shall arm myself with a street plan for orientation” - case 5 because the plan construction is a certain event that occured in the past outside your control. Alternatively, “I shall arm myself with a plan which outlines in advance where I am going to go and how I am going to spend my time and money” - case 2 or 4 depending on the certainty of said plans. Similarly, estimate may refer to either the past or the future. Past events often remain uncertain due to measurement error and other factors.</p>
<p>Having spent the better part of the last decade studying human behaviour and forecasting it under alternative conditions, I found Schumacher’s classification system encapsulated much of what I believe about the ability to forecast behaviour. I follow Schumacher’s definitions with a short commentary.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Full predictability (in principle) exists only in the absence of human freedom - i.e., in “sub-human” nature. The limitations of predictability are purely limitations of knowledge and technique.</li>
</ol>
<p>That is, if we assume no human freedom and deterministic choice, 100% accurate prediction is feasible provided we have all the available information and the correct model structure. I have the sense that many of my field are of the opinion that <em>Big Data</em> and <em>Artificial Intelligence</em> bring us daily closer to this reality. I am not so readily convinced of this fact.</p>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li>Relative predictability exists with regard to the behaviour pattern of large numbers of people doing “normal” things (routines).</li>
</ol>
<p>In transportation modeling, we would call this travel on a typical day and aggregate (4-step) demand modeling.</p>
<ol start="3" type="1">
<li>Relatively full predictability exists with regard to human actions controlled by a plan which eliminates freedom, e.g., railway timetables.</li>
</ol>
<p>I like this example for obvious reasons.</p>
<ol start="4" type="1">
<li>Individual decisions by individuals are in principle unpredictable.</li>
</ol>
<p>I agree with this statement. I see the shift towards disaggregate modeling as a means to increase prediction accuracy and nuance for large numbers of people (point 2 above) rather than a suggestion that we can accurately predict the individual decisions at which the model is set up.</p>
<p>Schumacher then touches on a point that has recently seen great interest in the transportation demand modeling community - uncertainty. He states “all long-term forecasting is somewhat presumptuous and absurd, unless it is of so general a kind that it merely states the obvious”. Schumacher emphasizes the need to focus on modeling as a tool for <em>exploratory calculations</em> rather than <em>forecasting</em>, per se. In forecasting, we are stating that a certain set of conditions will be the case in 20 years time or, in the slightly more nuanced form of the same, that differences from current conditions will have some absolute value. E.g., we forecast future traffic and make statements about the difference in traffic on particular roads given a change in infrastructure. An exploratory approach includes multiple potential futures and considers the “long-term effect of certain assumed tendencies”. Schumacher uses a development example. He proposes a backcasting exercise to explore potential pathways for the uplift of underdeveloped nations. “What would be the required output of foodstuffs, fuels, metals, textile fibres, and so forth? What would be the stock of industrial capital?” Many new assumptions would be necessarily along the way and the outcome would be a set of feasibility studies to indicate the most feasible among alternative <em>patterns of development</em>. The discussion here is again (partially) one of semantics. We must recognize that long-term forecasts are infeasible, while long-term feasibility study can be a worthwhile exercise.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>prediction</category>
  <category>estimation</category>
  <category>semantics</category>
  <guid>https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/05-28-2024/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 28 May 2024 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/05-28-2024/banner.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Jevons Paradox</title>
  <dc:creator>Jason Hawkins</dc:creator>
  <link>https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/04-26-2024/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>William Stanley Jevons was a 19th century English economist and logician. He made extensive contributions to the field, yet is perhaps best known for his eponymous paradox. Jevons Paradox arises when technological progress increases the efficiency with which a resource is used (reducing unit consumption), but the falling marginal cost of use induces increases in demand such that aggregate resource use is increased, rather than reduced. Engineers are, in general terms, believers in the benefits of technology. Efficiency gains are professed to solve any number of social and environmental ills. E.g., autonomous vehicles will solve traffic congestion and improved safety through their elimination of fallible human drivers. Consider the narrative regarding the population theory of another late 18th century/early 19th century economist - Thomas Malthus. Malthus predicted population collapse in response to population growth outstripping agricultural productivity growth. Thus far, his prediction has not come to pass partially due to technological progressing, including the 20th century Green Revolution (led by Norman Borlaug and others), which relieved starvation concerns - yay! Techno-optimists reference this success as an exemplar of why technology will save us. Furthermore, the so-called Environmental Kuznets Curve (named for yet another economist, Simon Kuznets) anticipates GDP becoming decoupled from environmental impacts as a nation moves from an industrial to a post-industrial economy.</p>
<p>Let us take a look at the Kuznets Curve in the context of Jevons Paradox. If we assume a steady state economy, then it may be the case that environmental impacts will decrease as a function of technological progress. By a steady state economy, we mean a constant stock of capital and fixed population.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/04-26-2024/jevons_1.svg" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-center figure-img" style="width:50.0%"></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Of course, we do not exist in a steady state economy, global population continues to grow (rising from 6 billiong to 8 billion people in my own lifetime). While natural resources are a fixed stock (we will return to this topic on many occassions), our rate of resource consumption has not declined as a function of technological progress. Rather, we continue to consume increasing quantities of materials and energy, which represent the fundamental building blocks of human society. Another way to term a steady state economy is that its size is a non-stationary function of time. Stationarity will be a familiar term to those with a background in statistics or econometrics - refering to the lack of equilibrium about a fixed level of resource consumption in this case. With GDP encouraged to grow without limit, Jevons Paradox quickly comes to bear. Technological progress will get us only so far when faced with the tasks of overcoming a non-stationarity system.</p>
<p>We can consider the problem from the perspective of aggregate environmental impact vs.&nbsp;marginal (unit) environmental impact. Jevons Paradox shows us that individuals will increase their environment impacts (vis-a-vis more consumption) in response to technological innovations that reduce the marginal cost, or material and energy requirements - i.e., increasing aggregate individual impacts. At the same time, additional individuals (i.e., population growth) compounds the impacts, even should these new individuals consume resources at a diminished rate.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-&quot;center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/04-26-2024/jevons_2.svg" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-&quot;center figure-img" style="width:50.0%"></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>So what can be done? The first step is to recognize myopia in our collective perspective on resource consumption as engineers, economists, policy-makers, and inhabitants of this planet. Classical valuation methods cannot account for these impacts, at least as long as they exist within an epistemology founded in growth as a positive property of human society rather than as a normative value.</p>
<p>I hope to continue to examine these topics in greater depth, not for professional promotion (unlikely absent a large grant to build ecological philosophy widgets with my graduate students) but rather for personal edification and sanity. I would like to reflect on value systems, morality, and social change. I am also interested in teasing out the seeming intangibles of the engineering perspective on policy evaluation from the conventional economics-based approach, and how engineering has been drawn into the economics perspective through a lack of appropriate application of relevant theory and knowledge - e.g., entropy, biophysical limits, and system dynamics.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>environmental economics</category>
  <category>system dynamics</category>
  <guid>https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/04-26-2024/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2024 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/04-26-2024/banner.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Four Horsemen of the Production Apocalypse</title>
  <dc:creator>Jason Hawkins</dc:creator>
  <link>https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/04-21-2024/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Gary Becker begins his “A Theory of the Allocation of Time” <span class="citation" data-cites="Becker_1965">(Becker 1965)</span> with a discussion of time spent at work relative to other activities, highlighting the need for more robust analyses of uncompensated time use in economics. Little did he know that his theory and model structure would strongly influence travel behaviour and economic analysis over subsequent decades. In the 1970s, DeSerpa <span class="citation" data-cites="DeSerpa_1971">(1971)</span> and Evans <span class="citation" data-cites="Evans_1972">(1972)</span> provided among the first connections to transportation analysis. Building from DeSerpa and Evans, Jara-Díaz <span class="citation" data-cites="Jara-Díaz_2003">(2003)</span> completed fundamental work on the value of time in transportation economics. However, there is a wealth of other insights relevant to transportation analysis to be gained from Becker’s theory. I will focus on the topic of transportation service provision.</p>
<p>Being a founder of the neoclassical “Chicago School of Economics”, Becker would certainly have strong opinions on the extension of his theory to include other non-market means of production. Nonetheless, one can consider four basic forms of production: market, home, government, and commons. Market production is the exchange of a good or service for money. Home production, as defined by Becker, is uncompensated production by the household (e.g., making dinner, cleaning the bathroom, etc.). The latter two forms of production were not discussed by Becker in his 1965 paper. In the first form, government produces a good or service for use by the public, financed by tax revenue or similar sources. For example, most healthcare services in the United States are privatized and subject to market forces, whereas many other nations provide healthcare as a public service. The final form of production is in the commons. Neoclassical economic theory suggests that common resources will be exploited if not managed by state intervention or market forces via monetization. However, both Mariana Mazzucato <span class="citation" data-cites="Mazzucato_2018">(2018)</span> and Elinor Ostrom <span class="citation" data-cites="Ostrom_1990">(1990)</span> provide compelling arguments for the efficient use of common production. As one example, Wikipedia is managed in the commons as most contributors provide their services at no cost.</p>
<p>The reader may wonder: what does any of this have to do with travel behaviour? I argue that the above economic production framework can be mapped onto the transportation mode choice problem and provides valuable insights for behavioural theory and modelling methods. Home production of transportation takes the form of walking, cycling, or using one’s own vehicle. The vehicle and fuel must be purchased on the market, but the transportation service is provided by the household using personal time as the only input to production. In contrast, taxi or ridehail modes are purchased in the market from private firms (e.g., Uber, Lyft, Didi, etc.). Government provides transportation as a public service through transit. Transportation provided in the commons is less common (a nice little pun) but takes the form of carsharing and other systems wherein the service cost is shared among a pool of otherwise unaffiliated households. Each of the above transportation alternatives could manifest as the same physical mode – i.e., a small passenger vehicle. However, the behavioural and operational models differ. For example, a person may be unable to afford market production (ridehail). They may not use public production (transit) to avoid sharing a vehicle with strangers. They may be unwilling to participate in the commons (carshare) because they don’t want someone’s muddy boots in their car.</p>
<p>Being trained as a civil engineer, I am always keen to find concrete (two puns in one article is the limit) applications for theory. The modelling of autonomous vehicles (AVs) provides an application of the above theory to transportation. Many scholars make the distinction between personal AVs, shared AVs (or SAVs) provided as a public service, and SAVs provided in the market. However, in my reading, there is minimal thought given to how these operating models would function from an economic production theory perspective. Let us first focus on the first alternative. It is unclear whether to classify a personal AV as home production or market consumption – Is sitting comfortably in a vehicle while it performs the driving task pure leisure? Are you purchasing driving services in the market as a software package? The latter two alternatives provide an interesting contrast. In both cases, SAVs are provided to the household as a service. However, if we consider transportation as a public service, another economic concept may be brought to bear, termed private provision of a public good by Bergstrom et al. <span class="citation" data-cites="Bergstrom_Blume_Varian_1986">(1986)</span> . Public transit provides a subsidized travel option for low-income households and those who choose not to own a personal vehicle. The widescale deployment of SAV fleets would therefore require ridehailing operators to take on this role. The risk is that each operator may rely on other operators to serve low-income households, with the result being a Nash equilibrium that does not maximize total social utility. Government intervention is necessary to ensure an equitable distribution of mobility through incentives or regulations <span class="citation" data-cites="Sieg_2020">(Sieg 2020)</span>. Existing simulations often ignore the profit-seeking motives of private operators, assuming they match trips to minimize detour time and are agnostic to traveller income and profit maximization motives on the part of operators.</p>
<p>As a final thought on the historical distinction between private and public travel modes. The marginal private automobile trip tends to add travel time for existing travellers through congestion that slows travel speed and increases its variability. In contrast, the marginal transit trip tends to improve service for existing travellers through reduced vehicle headways and the use of higher-order transit (i.e., trains rather than buses). The latter outcome is termed as an anti-congestion effect <span class="citation" data-cites="Mohring_1972">(Mohring 1972)</span>. The trend in SAV research is toward small, automobile-style, vehicles that may be shared or used alone. This shift adds shades of gray to the public-private dichotomy. Will shared mobility exhibit the congestion effect of fthe private automobile or the anti-congestion effect of transit? Importantly, in which contexts do these new forms of mobility tend to exhibit each of these effects (i.e., there is likely a spectrum of possible impacts depending on the application of technology, local built form, and transportation infrastructure conditions)?</p>
<section id="references" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="references">References</h2>
<div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-Becker_1965" class="csl-entry">
Becker, Gary S. 1965. <span>“A Theory of the Allocation of Time.”</span> <em>The Economic Journal</em> 75 (299): 493. <a href="https://doi.org/10.2307/2228949">https://doi.org/10.2307/2228949</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Bergstrom_Blume_Varian_1986" class="csl-entry">
Bergstrom, Theodore, Lawrence Blume, and Hal Varian. 1986. <span>“On the Private Provision of Public Goods.”</span> <em>Journal of Public Economics</em> 29: 2549.
</div>
<div id="ref-DeSerpa_1971" class="csl-entry">
DeSerpa, A. C. 1971. <span>“A Theory of the Economics of Time.”</span> <em>The Economic Journal</em> 81 (324): 828–46. <a href="https://doi.org/10.2307/2230320">https://doi.org/10.2307/2230320</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Evans_1972" class="csl-entry">
Evans, Alan W. 1972. <span>“On the Theory of the Valuation and Allocation of Time.”</span> <em>Scottish Journal of Political Economy</em> 19 (1): 1–17. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1467-9485.1972.tb00504.x">https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1467-9485.1972.tb00504.x</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Jara-Díaz_2003" class="csl-entry">
Jara-Díaz, Sergio R. 2003. <span>“On the Goods-Activities Technical Relations in the Time Allocation Theory.”</span> <em>Transportation</em> 30 (3): 245–60. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1023/A:1023936911351">https://doi.org/10.1023/A:1023936911351</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Mazzucato_2018" class="csl-entry">
Mazzucato, Mariana. 2018. <em>The Value of Everything: Making and Taking in the Global Economy: Mazzucato, Mariana: 9781610396745: Amazon.com: Books</em>. PublicAffairs.
</div>
<div id="ref-Mohring_1972" class="csl-entry">
Mohring, Herbert. 1972. <span>“Optimization and Scale Economies in Urban Bus Transportation.”</span> <em>The American Economic Review</em> 62 (4): 591–604. <a href="https://doi.org/10.2307/1806101">https://doi.org/10.2307/1806101</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Ostrom_1990" class="csl-entry">
Ostrom, Elinor. 1990. <em>Governing the Commons : The Evolution of Institutions for Collective Action</em>. Cambridge University Press. <a href="http://archive.org/details/governingcommons0000ostr">http://archive.org/details/governingcommons0000ostr</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Sieg_2020" class="csl-entry">
Sieg, Holger. 2020. <span>“Voluntary Provision of Local Public Goods and Services.”</span> In <em>Urban Economics and Fiscal Policy</em>, 90–105. Princeton University Press.
</div>
</div>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>transportation planning</category>
  <category>production theory</category>
  <guid>https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/04-21-2024/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 21 Apr 2024 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/04-21-2024/banner.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>William Vickrey and Transportation Economics</title>
  <dc:creator>Jason Hawkins</dc:creator>
  <link>https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/05-04-2018/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>William Vickrey made major contributions to a wide range of fields within the economics discipline and was recognized for his work with 1996 Nobel Prize in Economic Science. Many of his contributions fall within my interests of Urban and Transportation Economics, so I thought it worthwhile to review a few of his publications. He also happens to be the only Nobel Laureate, of which I am aware, who was borne in my home province of British Columbia. My focus will be on his work in marginal cost pricing, specifically his article “Congestion Theory and Transport Investment”, which was published in American Economic Review in 1969. This is among the first discussions of congestion pricing. His focus is on measures to relieve congestion, and the efficient allocation of public investment towards this objective. He suggests that investment does not sufficiently consider the marginal cost, and may therefore misrepresent consumer surplus as a metric for investment benefit.</p>
<p>Vickrey was one of those great geniuses who, in an off-hand comment, makes insights that would form the basis for an entire paper by others. One such case is that of bus headway, which he argued to be optimally related to demand by a square root relationship - to be proven analytically by Gordon Newell at UC Berkeley a few years later. Vickrey assumes delay to vary by the square of total volume, with no indication of an empirical reference point. This forms a cornerstone of his theory of traffic congestion. On average, a vehicle will inflict an amount of delay on other vehicles equal to the delay experienced by itself.</p>
<p>The principle situation of delay considered by Vickrey is what he terms a <em>bottleneck</em>. This is an instance of a segment of roadway that has a lower capacity than its upstream and downstream adjacent segments. The <em>bottleneck</em> is typically a function of a reduction in the number of travel lanes due to an accident or geometric constraint (e.g.&nbsp;bridge or road narrowing). Vickrey recognizes this is an atypical form of congestion, but argues for its tractable setup for analytical analysis of costs and measures of welfare.</p>
<p>He considers the example of a bottleneck on a roadway with a demand for travel of N = 7,200 commuters. It is assumed that their departure from the bottleneck is distributed uniformly over a period between <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t_a%20=%2008:00"> and <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t_b%20=%2009:00">. The critical capacity can be defined as</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%20v_m%20=%20%5Cfrac%7BN%7D%7Bt_b%20-%20t_a%7D%20=%20120%5C,%20veh/min%20%5Clabel%7Beq:mc1%7D%20"></p>
<p>If the capacity of the bottleneck is smaller than <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?v_m">, then it is impossible for all the commuters to reach their destinations at their desired arrival times. Some of the commuters will arrive at their destinations close to their arrival time, but will be required to stay in the queue for a longer time. While those who push their arrival time away from the desired arrival time, will spend relatively less time in the queue, but experience a penalty through time spent at home when they desire to be at their destination (or, if not desire, lose pay).</p>
<p>Vickrey makes a set of assumptions about value of time (VOT), which initially confused me on the basis of disutility of time - until I realized that they described activities with positive utility parameters. He defines the value of time spent at home at <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?w_h%20=%202%5C,%20cents/min">, time spent at work before the desired starting time at <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?w_o%20=%20w_p%20=%201%5C,%20cent/min">, and time spent at work after the desired starting time at <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?w_o%20=%20w_j%20=%204%5C,%20cents/min">. This means that, before the desired starting time, a person would rather be at home (greater VOT), while they would rather be at work after the desired start time. This tends to assume a wage of 2 cents per minute above the VOT for leisure (i.e.&nbsp;time spent at home). Time spent in the queue is valued at <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?w_q%20=%200%5C,%20cents/min">. With these monetary conditions, a fraction of commuters, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?r%20=%20%5Cfrac%7B2%7D%7B3%7D">, will pass through the queue during queue development. The time of maximum queue size will occur at <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t_p%20=%2008:40">, subjective to the above prices. Vickrey specifies a linear relationship for the queue size, producing a triangular shape in time and queue size, with a maximum at time <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t_p">. He suggests that a dynamic price structure be set, which eliminates the queue. The toll is set to zero at <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t_i"> and rises to a maximum, given by</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%20p_p%20=%20%5Cfrac%7BNr%7D%7Bv%7D(w_h%20-%20w_p)%20=%20%5Cfrac%7B4800%7D%7Bv%7D%20%5Clabel%7Beq:mc2%7D%20"></p>
<p>at <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t_p">, before falling to zero at <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t_j">. Commuters will leave their home at a time, such that they leave the location of the bottleneck at the same time they would leave the queue absent prices. This will distribute commuters throughout the time period in a more even manner, such that no queue forms and no commuter would be better off changing their departure time, in terms of VOT and congestion toll.</p>
<p>An interesting aspect to this result is that it has a net neutral effect from the perspective of the commuter, but produces additional revenue for the local government agency levying the toll. Revenue from the toll could be used to offset an existing flat toll or invested in long-term infrastructure improvements (e.g.&nbsp;transit or capacity expansion). Vickrey extends his study through empirical analysis of the results, consideration of alternative routes, and variation in the VOT. He provides some interesting commentary on the assessment of investments in new infrastructure. He argues that many of the new routes put forth at the time of publication based their benefit measures on increased speeds and flow volumes. These are not accurate measures of benefits to the user because they are frequently circuitous routes and do not decrease overall travel time. Vickrey argues for the application of congestion pricing as a policy lever in the cost-benefit analysis. The inclusion of such a measure would give a more accurate picture of the monetized improvement in travel time.</p>
<p>Vickrey published “The City as a Firm” in the proceedings of a conference held by the International Economic Association in 1977. The significance of this work is its early development of concepts of New Economic Geography. Vickrey identifies the importance of transportation costs and economies of scale as model inputs. The absence of transportation costs represents a futuristic notion of instantaneous movement of goods and persons. Vickrey defines economies of scale in this context as positive neighbourhood effects. This is a measure of the efficiency of proximity. If each activity could be carried out efficiently within small shops, then production could be uniformly spread throughout a region without loss of efficiency. Evidence has found neither to be the case and this is an important point in the context of autonomous vehicles (AV). They are often touted as significantly reducing transportation costs, but this argument fails on two counts. Based on the arguments of Vickrey, this argument fails to recognize the structural importance of scale economies. Such effects are wholly unaffected by the introduction of AV and economic efficiency will outweigh any desire to relocate activities to more dispersed locations. Vickrey discusses the importance of natural features in the location of our largest cities, while also recognizing that their size would be far smaller in the absence of economies of scale.</p>
<p>A related publication, in the context of the effect of AV adoption on city formation, is the book “Peak Car: the Future of Travel” by Professor David Metz at UCL. He provides a strong argument for hard limits on the speed of travel within an urbanized region. Metz argues that average commuting time has an equilibrium about 30 minutes, going back to the dawn of human civilization. While not a new argument, it is an important one and has been largely overlooked in the AV literature. These vehicles have the potential to introduce marginal increases in travel speed and therefore travel distance, but this 30 minute threshold will likely remain. Transportation costs will remain a factor in the formation and development of urban regions.</p>
<p>Vickrey assumes a perfect market in developing a model of the city as a firm but recognizes this is not an ideal assumption. Dixit and Stiglitz published their monopolistic competition model in the same year, which led to the NEG work of Krugman in the following decades (for which he scored himself a Nobel).</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>economics</category>
  <category>Canadians</category>
  <guid>https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/05-04-2018/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 04 May 2018 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/05-04-2018/banner.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Our Trip to Toronto Through the USA</title>
  <dc:creator>Jason Hawkins</dc:creator>
  <link>https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/09-11-2017/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Written after we crossed the country for my Ph.D.&nbsp;in 2017. I haven’t returned to Duluth, MN yet…</p>
<p>We just completed an exhausting 1 week tour of the northern states: North Dakota, Minnesota, Wisconsin, and Michigan. One of the major take aways for both Heather and myself was the various infrastructure we traversed in the course of our travels. I would like to discuss a bit of this, with some accomonying amateur photography.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>This was the best case of a roller joint on a steel frame structure I have ever seen. It bring back mixed feelings about days in Structure Engineering courses during my undergraduage degree. <img src="https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/09-11-2017/DSC_0891.JPG" class="img-fluid" alt="Grand Forks, ND Bridge"></li>
<li>This was a mediocre brewery, but a great spot in Grand Forks, ND. It is situated adjacent to a major rail corridor and take full advantange. There are clear views of the trains rolling into town and by the brewery thanks to large windows looking out onto the street and alley. It was an excellent example of linking the present use of an older structure with its surrounding environment and historical industrial roots. <img src="https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/09-11-2017/img/DSC_0897.JPG" class="img-fluid" alt="Grand Forks, ND Brewery"></li>
<li>We drove into Duluth, MN with very little knowledge of its layout and no plans as to what to visit. This is I35 passing through downtown. We pulled off the highway at a downtown exit and planned to walk somewhere for lunch. This rapidly became more of a challenge than expected as it turned out the downtown is largely commercial and wayfinding signage proved less than helpful. The interstate acts to separate the downtown from the lakeshore. It is unclear from this side of the interstate whether there are additional services on the lakeshore side of the roadway and it is clearly prohibitive to pedestrians. We were able to find a pedestrian overpass to the lakeshore, which led to a quaint lakeside retail area. We were able to find an excellent brewery (sense a pattern) called Canal Park Brewing Company. I noticed a similar patttern of the commercial centre being separated from the tourist-focused lakeshore upon arrival in Toronto. This is a model reminiscent of the days of Robert Moses in New York, with his focus on placing large-scale transportation facilities along prime waterfront real estate. <img src="https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/09-11-2017/DSC_0946.JPG" class="img-fluid" alt="Duluth Interstate"></li>
<li>We were unable to ride the train, but it gives some incentive to return to the Duluth, MN area. It promises excellent views of the Lake Superior shore and ends at Two Harbors, MN. It feels like a disservice to my profession to miss out on an historical train ride. <img src="https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/09-11-2017/DSC_0950.JPG" class="img-fluid" alt="Duluth Train"></li>
</ol>



 ]]></description>
  <category>travel</category>
  <category>infrastructure</category>
  <guid>https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/09-11-2017/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 11 Sep 2017 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/09-11-2017/banner.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>AV Deployment, Urban DNA, and Equity</title>
  <dc:creator>Jason Hawkins</dc:creator>
  <link>https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/07-03-2017/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><em>Written before starting my Ph.D.&nbsp;in 2017 (July 03, 2017)…</em></p>
<p>Many questions arise for the transportation-land use modeller with the prospect of autonomous vehicles. Its effect on urban form will be heavily influenced by the manner in which it is implemented. It is probable AV will become a ubiquitous replacement of our current auto fleet, but may not be placed under personal ownership. One alternative would be a public fleet of vehicles. This has the advantage of being controlled by a single entity with a history of managing shared mobility services. Given the rapid emergence of the technology and its beginning in the private sector via automobile and technology firms, it is also likely for AV to be implemented as a set of competing services, similar to Uber and Lyft. This has advantages from the perspective of competition leading to innovation, but raises equity concerns. In addition, by placing the means of transport into private hands, there are concerns raised about privatization of infrastructure, etc. The final alternative would be a simple replacement of private automobiles, with personal ownership of each AV. These alternative implementations have the potential to influence the impact of AV on urban form.</p>
<p>My thoughts on this matter are concentrated on representing these alternative implementations in an integrated modelling framework. Do existing model frameworks have the capacity to model such changes, or are new methods required? The LUTI modelling field developed within a relatively stable transport system (i.e.&nbsp;the private automobile paradym). There is likely a need for increased dynamics in models. Rather than examining the impacts on demand of the introduction of a new interchange, we are interested in the changes in urban form resulting from a change in transportation supply and associated changes in demand. Alan Wilson is one of the founders of spatial interaction models and continues to develop innovative ideas with regards to dynamics in urban systems and their basic form. One of th concepts he considers is the idea of an urban ‘DNA’ and introduction of concepts from biological evolution into urban modelling. These types of concepts are critical in the development of models with the ability to consider seemingly large deviations from our current systems of transport. This requires a concept of fundamental rules of urban formation and growth to be operationalized in the model and not allowing oneself to be constrained by current transportation modes, etc.</p>
<p>One of the structures attributed to the introduction of the private automobile is urban sprawl, but to the history nerd this form appears long before. Without dipping too deep into history, we can see similar forms in the country estates of 18th century Britain. The ‘London Season’ was a time of the year when these nobles and other wealthy property owners would come into the city for a time to meet and put together marriages. We seem to have a natural, in our DNA, preference for solitude and personal space. Conversely, we also require proximity for social engagement, even with our rapidly developing communication technologies. Increased wealth among the middle classes has brought the ability to own a small ‘estate’ within the grasps of the every man, suggesting urban sprawl is not only a function of the automobile, but an ingrained desire that became possible through increased wealth. In the context of AV, I wonder what ingrained, DNA-based, desires and preferences will manifest themselves in our urban form. I perceive a need for better longitudinal data analysis, rather than close calibration to data from the current year. Rather than forcing the spatial structures of today onto the model, we should focus on dynamics and long-term trends. I have more confidence in the stability of the human mind than a concrete overpass with a 50 year design life, built 40 years ago. We must look to analogy in the phyical sciences in physics and biological DNA, but remember we humans are complex and dynamic systems. We should also be considering the latest concepts in economics and psychology. We must not allow ourselves to be pulled into the stream of past models, but let them guide us.</p>
<p><em>Written at the start of my Ph.D.&nbsp;(Nov.&nbsp;27, 2017)…</em></p>
<p>One aspect of AV, which has not be sufficiently assessed is the issue of social equity. Mobility is a key factor in determining social mobility (excuse the word-play) and there is strong evidence for transportation investment/quality being strongly correlated with the spatial distribution of income groups. In terms of transit usage, higher income groups tend to take fixed rail transit over bus. This has resulted in the subway map of many cities displaying a strong resemblance with income maps (see for example this CityLab article). Transportation comprises about 30% of household expenses for the poorest of North Americans.</p>
<p>This brings us to the case of AV. Some believe this innovation will be unequivocally good for equity. They expect vehicle prices to fall and anticipate implementation as a shared mobility-as-a-service system. The thinking is that the sharing of the cost of a ride will decrease the marginal cost of a trip and lower the access cost for lower income households. The cost of ownership will be shared between users and the removal of the driving task will drastically lower operating costs relative to taxis. This line of thinking is in contrast with some fundamental principles of economics that I will discuss below.</p>
<p>First, we must consider that this proposed service will have substantial sunk cost research associated with it. Technology development is expensive and we are not looking at a government agency, which will utilize tax revenues to pursue research for public benefit. These are large publically held corporations, with the mandate of maximizing shareholder revenue. Absent of government intervention via subsidies, initial AV trips will be expensive and available to the wealthy. Rudimentary microeconomics states that this is the path of any non-inferior good: consumption will increase with increasing available capital.</p>
<p>I would like to provide an example to structure the argument. Consider a vehicle with capacity for 5 occupants. A firm can choose to 1) charge $1 for each passenger in order to provide a service available to all residents of the city or 2) charge $4 for each passenger, knowing that a large segment of the population will be excluded from the service. In order for case 1 to govern, the firm must be certain of at least 4 passengers for each trip. As a risk averse agent, the firm will invariably decided to charge $4 knowing they only need to capture a single rider for each trip to break even with respect to case 1. Additional passengers will rapidly increase the profits of the firm beyond what could be provided under case 1. This brings us back to the issue of equity and its spatial component. If we assume that there is spatial segregation by income group (a very reasonable assumption), we can say that $4 trips will be concentrated in set of sub-regions within the city. We can consider a situation of $4 “trip signals” for a high income sub-region and $1 “trip signals” from a low income sub-region. The shared mobility operator, seeking to optimize their vehicle routing, will deploy the majority of their vehicles in areas where they can maximize their profits - a function of the demand for trips at the prevailing rate of service.</p>
<p>AV and mobility-as-a-service raise questions about willingness-to-pay and willingness-to-share. Absent government input, these services will act solely based on market forces. Current patterns of auto ownership and usage suggest people would be willing to pay a substantial premium to avoid vehicle sharing. In a culture of 1.20 vehicle occupancies, can we consider shared mobility as a likely outcome? Profit seeking private vehicle operators will have no qualms about circulating vehicles through upper income communities where the highest premium can be gained for each trip. This will exclude lower income households from use of the service. Lower operating costs does not necessarily mean that prices will drop. The price of a trip will be a function of the willingness-to-pay for each person and the number of persons who are willing to pay a given price, that is aggregate demand. It may be the case that operators can maintain sufficient ridership at high prices and not require a lower price to draw in additional ridership. Each vehicle will still constitute a capital cost and firms will seek to maximize unit (vehicle) profit and technology costs will be high for each vehicle.</p>
<p>I do not argue that prices will not come down eventually, but the risk is that during the period of partial AV penetration barriers will form that exclude, or inhibit, the adoption of this new mobility tool by lower income households. Consideration of equity in transportation and land use model forecasts will be critical in informing government policy to mitigate these effects. I have seen the effects of transportation on social exclusion through my travels in South America and even here in Canada and the United States. These considerations will be particularly important in developing cities, where government incentive structures may differ from what we see in North American cities. Work conducted with the PECAS model framework in Caracas, Venezuala has proven the ability of these tools to quantify the equity challenges of transportation policy. We need only examine the locations where AV testing is currently taking place to see the potential inequity in its service provision. Major testing is occuring in Palo Alto and other technology hubs, among Richard Florida’s Creative Class - engineers, software developers, and the like. AV adoption has the potential to alleviate issues of accessibility and inequity of access, but we cannot negate the possibility of it exacerbating these problems in an environment of market-driven mobility.</p>
<p>Some final thoughts on the topic: How will luxury services affect access to AV? There is the potential for segregation of the market and higher quality services made available to those who can afford them. As infrastructure evolves to meet the needs of AV, I question whether this evolution will occur uniformly through the city or be focused in higher income communities where residents have the social capital to influence policy and the financial capital to become early adopters of the technology.</p>
<p><em>Written during my Ph.D.&nbsp;(Nov.&nbsp;30, 2018)…</em> A great source of inspiration in my thinking this past year has been the podcast EconTalk with Russ Roberts. This week Russ spoke with the Political Economist Michael Munger about his new book “Tomorrow 3.0: Transaction Costs and the Sharing Economy” and, more generally, the sharing economy. Their discussion raised some questions for me around my own research in transportation and land use. Michael placed great emphasis on the importance of transaction costs, which include and bear a close resemblance to transportation costs and accessibility. Michael defines transactions costs into three, conveniently ‘t-suffixed’ words, namely: triangulation, transfer, and trust. He gives the case of the Sears catalogue as an early 20th century example of reducing transaction costs. The catalogue provided a medium for the aggregation of a wide variety of goods for sale. The Sears catalogue can be argued to be a predecessor of Amazon. Both represented major leaps forward in our ability to reduce transaction costs. The goods are provided in a centralized location (fulfilling triangulation), low cost in their distribution networks (transfer), and trusted by consumers. The ability to rate suppliers is a key ingredient in the success of Amazon and, focusing on the shared economy, the emergence of software that provides a means of trust in non-traditional market transactions. Consider Uber, which provides a service similar to hitchhiking in its lack of regulation. Users trust the service because Uber acts as an intermediary system of vetting for drivers.</p>
<p>Michael and Russ spend the first portion of the podcast talking about the sharing economy and the cost of durable goods. There are many goods we rarely use (e.g.&nbsp;power tools), which could be rented rather than owned. The main criteria for an effective shared durable good is that it have a high purchase price and low frequency of use. Michael provides an example of autonomous vehicles transporting rented equipment between homes, which is intriguing but also MIGHT presents challenges with respect to road congestion. I say might because it is not straightforward to compare individuals making purchases at the store with a centralized provider of goods, who can potentially optimize their route planning and carry many goods in a single vehicle. There are interesting questions around where the tradeoff lies between the cost of ownership and the cost of rental, including transportation costs.</p>
<p>One point that stood out for me in their discussion was the space requirement for durable goods. The primary examples are cars and large power tools. They discuss how space requirements for dwellings might be reduced by a diminished storage requirement within the home. Mind blown! It is so intuitive, but yet is not something I have considered at length. I am a great hoarder of books, which take up precious shelf space in our small apartment. The library is a (very) old example of the sharing economy in this particular space. I generally take advantage of this resource but the transaction costs are high for the cost of the good: I need to be sure the book is available at my local branch or reserve the book - requiring a wait for the satisfaction of reading a particular book. I’m often rough with my books, adding to my preference for ownership. None the less, it raises interesting questions about the reduction in building footprint associated with the shared ownership of cars, and perhaps other large durable goods.</p>
<p>Michael and Russ talk about Uber being a framework for sharing, well outside the transportation realm. I think this evolution is highly probable and it raises some fascinating questions for transportation and land use researchers. These are fundamentally questions of transportation, accessibility, proximity, and time - in the parlance of my field. It is an exciting time to begin in this field, indeed!</p>
<p>My usual notes on these topics: how will these new technologies affect equity? How can new technologies be framed in the context of networks? This is a topic I am ruminating on as a potential book idea. I have an enormous passion for history, which is largely untapped in my research. I have been thinking a lot about topics for a book that mix my interest in history with the perspective of a Transportation Engineer. We shall see where it leads…</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>technology</category>
  <category>autonomous vehicles</category>
  <category>equity</category>
  <guid>https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/07-03-2017/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 03 Jul 2017 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://Hawkins-TECH-Lab.github.io/hawkins-tech-lab.github.io/thoughts/posts/07-03-2017/banner.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
